<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<akn:akomaNtoso xmlns:akn="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0">
  <akn:act>
    <akn:meta>
      <akn:identification source="#cosilico">
        <akn:FRBRWork prescriptive="true" authoritative="true">
          <akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-sd/act/code/title28/main" />
          <akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-sd/act/code/title28" />
          <akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="enactment" />
          <akn:FRBRauthor href="#sdleg" />
          <akn:FRBRcountry value="us-sd" />
        </akn:FRBRWork>
        <akn:FRBRExpression>
          <akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-sd/act/code/title28/eng@2025-12-31/main" />
          <akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-sd/act/code/title28/eng@2025-12-31" />
          <akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="publication" />
          <akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" />
          <akn:FRBRlanguage language="en" />
        </akn:FRBRExpression>
        <akn:FRBRManifestation>
          <akn:FRBRthis value="/akn/us-sd/act/code/title28/eng@2025-12-31/main.akn" />
          <akn:FRBRuri value="/akn/us-sd/act/code/title28/eng@2025-12-31.akn" />
          <akn:FRBRdate date="2025-12-31" name="transformation" />
          <akn:FRBRauthor href="#cosilico" />
        </akn:FRBRManifestation>
      </akn:identification>
    </akn:meta>
    <akn:body>
      <akn:part eId="title_28">
        <akn:num>Title 28</akn:num>
        <akn:heading>Public Welfare and Assistance</akn:heading>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_1">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-1</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>State Department of Social Services</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_1">
            <akn:num>28-1-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Duties of department--System of social security--Compliance with federal acts--Administration of programs</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-1
.
Duties of department--System of social security--Compliance with federal acts--Administration of programs.
The Department of Social Services shall provide a system of social security for the people of South Dakota, enable the State of South Dakota to comply with the provisions of the federal Social Security Act and other federal and state enactments relating to social services, accept grants of federal funds for the purposes enumerated in these acts, administer programs for the security and protection of children, youth, families, adults, and the elderly, as authorized by the Legislature, and provide moneys necessary for the purposes of social security.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 55.3601; SL 1981, ch 199, § 25.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_2">
            <akn:num>28-1-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 8</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-2
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 8.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_3">
            <akn:num>28-1-3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-3</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-3.
Superseded</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_3_1">
            <akn:num>28-1-3.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-3</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-3.1.
Superseded</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_3_2">
            <akn:num>28-1-3.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 9</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-3.2
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 9.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_4">
            <akn:num>28-1-4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-4</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-4.
Repealed by SL 1971, ch 23, § 2</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_5">
            <akn:num>28-1-5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-5 to 28-1-7</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-5 to 28-1-7.
Superseded</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_8">
            <akn:num>28-1-8</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-8</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-8.
Repealed by SL 1969, ch 218, § 2</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_9">
            <akn:num>28-1-9</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 10</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-9
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 10.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_10">
            <akn:num>28-1-10</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-10</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-10.
Superseded</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_11">
            <akn:num>28-1-11</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Assistant attorney general for department--Enforcement of support and public assistance laws--Representation of department</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-11
.
Assistant attorney general for department--Enforcement of support and public assistance laws--Representation of department.
The attorney general shall appoint an assistant attorney general for the Department of Social Services whose compensation shall be fixed by the attorney general, to be paid from public welfare funds.
Subject to the direction of the attorney general, the assistant attorney general shall supervise the enforcement of all laws pertaining to desertion, nonsupport, recipient fraud, and similar statutes for which a penalty is provided in any case in which public assistance has been granted or applied for under the welfare laws of this state. The assistant attorney general shall cooperate with and assist the several state's attorneys of the State of South Dakota in such actions and proceedings; be the official information agent for the State of South Dakota pursuant to chapter
25-9C
; and initiate and prosecute civil and criminal actions on behalf of the Department of Social Services, and appear on behalf of the department in any court in which any action or proceeding is pending involving the welfare of the indigent.
Source:
SL 1963, ch 333; SL 1966, ch 169; SL 2004, ch 167, § 12; SL 2015, ch 148, § 83.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_12">
            <akn:num>28-1-12</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Office space and equipment provided for department by county commissioners</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-12
.
Office space and equipment provided for department by county commissioners.
Upon request of the Department of Social Services, the boards of county commissioners of the several counties of this state may provide and maintain adequate office space and equipment for the department in their respective counties including all of the incidental expenses thereof, except for the salaries and travel expenses of the employees of the department. The boards of county commissioners may make such expenditures as are necessary for such offices out of the county general fund.
Source:
SL 1963, ch 53; SL 1965, ch 29; SL 2004, ch 167, § 13.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_13">
            <akn:num>28-1-13</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-13</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-13.
Superseded</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_13_1">
            <akn:num>28-1-13.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 11</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-13.1
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 11.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_13_2">
            <akn:num>28-1-13.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-13</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-13.2.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 166, § 24</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_14">
            <akn:num>28-1-14</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, §§ 12 to 14</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-14
to 28-1-16.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, §§ 12 to 14.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_17">
            <akn:num>28-1-17</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-17</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-17.
Repealed by SL 2004, ch 167, § 17</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_18">
            <akn:num>28-1-18</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Duplication of public assistance prohibited--Temporary assistance for needy families excepted--Exhaustion of other sources of assistance as prerequisite to state and local assistance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-18
.
Duplication of public assistance prohibited--Temporary assistance for needy families excepted--Exhaustion of other sources of assistance as prerequisite to state and local assistance.
No person receiving a grant or whose needs are included in a grant under public assistance, as administered by the State of South Dakota, may at the same time receive a grant under any other type of public assistance administered by the State of South Dakota. However, a recipient of one of the other types of assistance may be the payee of a grant of temporary assistance for needy families for the benefit of a child or children under the payee's care. No person is eligible for any assistance or services from the State of South Dakota or its agencies or subdivisions until that person has exhausted all other sources of assistance or services available to the person or for which the person would be eligible if the person applied, including Veteran's Administration benefits, insurance, medical or hospital benefits, third
-
party liability, U.S. Public Health Services, Bureau of Indian Affairs, Department of Interior, Indian Health Service, or any other government or private entity, or any assistance or services provided by any agency of the United States government to an eligible person or to persons for whom the United States is responsible. Assistance or services under chapter
28-13
are not available sources for the purpose of this section.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 302; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.36
12-1
; SL 1982, ch 213, § 2; SL 2004, ch 167, § 18.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_19">
            <akn:num>28-1-19</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-19 to 28-1-24</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-19 to 28-1-24.
Repealed by SL 1983, ch 215, §§ 1 to 6</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_24_1">
            <akn:num>28-1-24.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Procedural rules for contested cases</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-24.1
.
Procedural rules for contested cases.
The secretary of social services may adopt reasonable and necessary rules governing the procedure and conduct of contested cases. Such rules shall be consistent with the procedure required by chapter
1-26
.
Source:
SL 1981, ch 199, § 26.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_25">
            <akn:num>28-1-25</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Protective payment of assistance where recipient incapable</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-25
.
Protective payment of assistance where recipient incapable.
In cases where recipients of public assistance are wasteful or unable to manage the receipt and disbursement of assistance payments so as to substantially accomplish the purposes for which such assistance is given, the Department of Social Services may protectively pay the same in such manner as to best provide the maintenance of such recipients.
Source:
SL 1966, ch 192.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_26">
            <akn:num>28-1-26</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, §§ 15, 16</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-26
, 28-1-27.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, §§ 15, 16.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_28">
            <akn:num>28-1-28</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Civil action for reimbursement from persons responsible for support</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-28
.
Civil action for reimbursement from persons responsible for support.
Whenever any payment of public moneys administered by the Department of Social Services has been made to any person who has been granted public aid or assistance, the department may bring a civil action against any person responsible therefor, as provided by law, to recover such moneys as have been paid for support or aid.
Source:
SL 1963, ch 334; SL 2004, ch 167, § 19.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_28_1">
            <akn:num>28-1-28.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Department acceptance and administration of private support contributions--Use</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-28.1
.
Department acceptance and administration of private support contributions--Use.
The Department of Social Services may accept and administer private support contributions received from responsible relatives and other sources, whether paid pursuant to the voluntary agreement of a contributor, or as provided by a court of competent jurisdiction. Such receipts shall be deposited with the state treasurer and shall be used only for the support, or reimbursement of support advanced, of the individual for whom designated. No money received by the state treasurer pursuant to this section may revert to the general fund of the state.
Source:
SL 2004, ch 167, § 40.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_29">
            <akn:num>28-1-29</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Public assistance records confidential--Exceptions</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_29__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>For inspection by any person duly authorized by this state or the United States in connection with the person's official duties;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_29__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>For the purpose of fair hearings as provided by law.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 55.3622; SL 1941, ch 311; SL 1953, ch 295, § 1; SL 2004, ch 167, § 20.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_30">
            <akn:num>28-1-30</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-30</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-30.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 166, § 24</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_31">
            <akn:num>28-1-31</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Adoption and child placement records remain confidential</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-31
.
Adoption and child placement records remain confidential.
Nothing contained in §
28-1-29
may be construed to authorize or require the disclosure of any records of the Department of Social Services pertaining to adoptions or pertaining to children placed in foster homes for adoption or other purposes.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 55.3622 as added by SL 1953, ch 295, § 1; SL 2004, ch 167, § 21.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_32">
            <akn:num>28-1-32</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Rules governing custody, use and preservation of records--Use in actions involving public officers and employees</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-32
.
Rules governing custody, use and preservation of records--Use in actions involving public officers and employees.
The department shall, by rules promulgated pursuant to chapter
1-26
, establish and enforce reasonable rules governing the custody, use, and preservation of the records, papers, files, and communications of the state and county divisions. The provisions of this section do not prevent the proper use of such records as evidence in civil or criminal actions by or against state or county officers and employees or their sureties involving the use or misuse of public funds or confidential records, or misfeasance or malfeasance in office.
Source:
SL 1941, ch 326, § 1; SL 1953, ch 295, § 2; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.36
22-1
; SL 2004, ch 167, § 22.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_33">
            <akn:num>28-1-33</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Unauthorized use of public assistance records as misdemeanor</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-33
.
Unauthorized use of public assistance records as misdemeanor.
It is a Class 2 misdemeanor for any person, except as provided in §§
28-1-29
to
28-1-31
, inclusive, to solicit, disclose, receive, make use of, or authorize, knowingly permit, participate in, or acquiesce in the use of any information concerning persons applying for or receiving public assistance, directly or indirectly derived from the records, papers, files, or communications of the state or county or subdivision or agency thereof, or acquired in the course of the performance of official duties.
Source:
SL 1941, ch 326, §§ 2, 3; SL 1953, ch 295, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, §§ 55.36
22-2
(1), 55.9935; SDCL, §
28-1-35
; SL 2004, ch 167, § 23.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_34">
            <akn:num>28-1-34</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Commercial and political use of public assistance records as misdemeanor</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-34
.
Commercial and political use of public assistance records as misdemeanor.
It is a Class 2 misdemeanor for any person to make use of any lists or names of public assistance recipients for commercial or political purposes.
Source:
SL 1941, ch 326, §§ 2, 3; SL 1953, ch 295, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, §§ 55.36
22-2
(2), 55.9935; SDCL, §
28-1-35
; SL 2004, ch 167, § 24.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_35">
            <akn:num>28-1-35</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-35</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-35.
Superseded</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_36">
            <akn:num>28-1-36</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 17</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-36
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 17.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_37">
            <akn:num>28-1-37</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-37</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-37.
Repealed by SL 1982, ch 16, § 20</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_38">
            <akn:num>28-1-38</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-38</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-38.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 199, § 27</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_39">
            <akn:num>28-1-39</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-39</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-39.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 167, § 2</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_40">
            <akn:num>28-1-40</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-40</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-40.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 199, § 29</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_41">
            <akn:num>28-1-41</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 18</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-41
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 18.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_42">
            <akn:num>28-1-42</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-42, 28-1-43</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-42, 28-1-43.
Repealed by SL 2004, ch 167, §§ 27, 28</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_44">
            <akn:num>28-1-44</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Transferred to §§ 1-36A-25 to 1-36A-28</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-44
to 28-1-45.2.
Transferred to §§
1-36A-25
to
1-36A-28
.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_45_3">
            <akn:num>28-1-45.3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, §§ 19, 20</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-45.3
, 28-1-45.4.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, §§ 19, 20.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_45_5">
            <akn:num>28-1-45.5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Transferred to § 1-36A-29</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-45.5
.
Transferred to §
1-36A-29
.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_45_6">
            <akn:num>28-1-45.6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 21</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-45.6
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 21.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_45_7">
            <akn:num>28-1-45.7</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Transferred to § 1-36A-30</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-45.7
.
Transferred to §
1-36A-30
.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_46">
            <akn:num>28-1-46</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Low-income energy assistance program--Agreements with other public agencies for establishment</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-46
.
Low
-
income energy assistance program--Agreements with other public agencies for establishment.
The Department of Social Services may enter into agreements with agencies of the United States and with other public agencies, as defined in subdivision 1-24-1(2), for the purpose of establishing and administering a low
-
income energy assistance program.
Source:
SL 1981, ch 199, § 18.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_47">
            <akn:num>28-1-47</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-47</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-47.
Repealed by SL 2017, ch 1, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_48">
            <akn:num>28-1-48</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Citizens returning from abroad--Agreements with federal agencies for participation</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-48
.
Citizens returning from abroad--Agreements with federal agencies for participation.
The Department of Social Services may enter into agreements with agencies of the United States for the purpose of participating in the program of temporary assistance for American citizens returned from abroad (P.L. 94-44).
Source:
SL 1981, ch 199, § 20.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_49">
            <akn:num>28-1-49</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Payments to recipients of supplemental security income--Establishment program</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-49
.
Payments to recipients of supplemental security income--Establishment program.
The Department of Social Services shall establish a program for payment of an optional state supplement to recipients of supplemental security income from the federal government.
Source:
SL 1981, ch 199, § 21.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_50">
            <akn:num>28-1-50</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Rules for administration and operation of programs</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_50__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Eligibility criteria;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_50__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Levels of payment;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_50__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Administration, audit requirements, and record keeping; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_50__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Such other standards and requirements as may be necessary for federal financial participation.
Source:
SL 1981, ch 199, § 22.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_51">
            <akn:num>28-1-51</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Rules for protection of confidential information</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-51
.
Rules for protection of confidential information.
The secretary of social services may adopt reasonable and necessary rules to protect records and confidential information required by statutory law to be held confidential.
Source:
SL 1981, ch 199, § 24.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_52">
            <akn:num>28-1-52</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Fiscal impact of department rules on local government units restricted</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-52
.
Fiscal impact of department rules on local government units restricted.
The Department of Social Services may not promulgate rules which have a negative fiscal impact on units of local government unless specifically authorized by the Legislature.
Source:
SL 1981, ch 199, § 23; SL 2004, ch 167, § 36.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_53">
            <akn:num>28-1-53</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 22</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-53
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, § 22.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_54">
            <akn:num>28-1-54</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-54 to 28-1-58</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-54 to 28-1-58.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 166, § 24</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_59">
            <akn:num>28-1-59</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Injury, disease, or death of work activity participant--Eligibility for medical and disability benefits</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-59
.
Injury, disease, or death of work activity participant--Eligibility for medical and disability benefits.
A recipient of public assistance who incurs permanent partial disability, permanent total disability, death, or disease in the course of participation in a work activity is entitled to the same benefits as are set forth for work related injuries and diseases in Title 62. This provision does not include payment of medical expenses unless those expenses are necessitated by a permanent disability or disease. Eligibility for other public funded medical benefits shall reduce entitlement to medical benefits under this section accordingly. In order to receive the above
-
referenced disability benefits, a work activity participant must comply with all of the employee notice, reporting, and medical examination requirements set forth in Title 62. The initial report of injury shall be submitted by the work activity participant in writing to the Department of Social Services.
Source:
SL 1982, ch 202, § 2A; SL 1997, ch 166, § 25.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_60">
            <akn:num>28-1-60</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Child care services program</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-60
.
Child care services program.
The Department of Social Services shall establish a program of child care services to assist families with child care services and to aid in the improvement of quality and services for the care of children in day care. The department may assist in the improvement, availability, and quality of day care for children by providing training, education, and advocacy for child care.
Source:
SL 1991, ch 222, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_61">
            <akn:num>28-1-61</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Adoption of rules for child care services program</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Eligibility determination, criteria, and application procedure;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The amount, scope, and duration of child care services and payments;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Fees;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Licensing and registration;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Methods of administration, record keeping, and audit;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Compliance monitoring;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Complaint investigation;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Reporting requirements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_9">
              <akn:num>(9)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Eligibility criteria and procedures for grants, contracts, and awards to providers of child care services under §
28-1-60
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_10">
              <akn:num>(10)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Training, community and provider education, and child advocacy; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_61__subsec_11">
              <akn:num>(11)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Such other standards and requirements as may be necessary to ensure the efficient operation and administration of the program or as required to qualify for federal funding.
Source:
SL 1991, ch 222, § 2.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_62">
            <akn:num>28-1-62</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, §§ 23, 24</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-62
, 28-1-63.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 151, §§ 23, 24.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_64">
            <akn:num>28-1-64</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Payments by public agencies to adoptive parents with limited means--Costs covered--Rules</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-64
.
Payments by public agencies to adoptive parents with limited means--Costs covered--Rules.
The provisions of §
25-6-13
concerning the parents' financial ability to the contrary notwithstanding, the Department of Social Services or any other public agency may make payments as needed in behalf of a child with special needs after placement for adoption, including the necessary costs of the legal completion of the child's adoption. The department may make these payments if the family has the capability of providing the permanent family relationships needed by the child in all areas except financial, as determined by the department or a licensed child placement agency. It shall also be determined that the needs of the child are beyond the economic ability and resources of the family and that the child would go without adoption except for the acceptance of the child as a member of the adoptive family or that the child would become dependent upon the state for support. Such payments to adoptive parents may include maintenance costs, medical and surgical expenses, and other costs incidental to the care of the child. Payments for maintenance, medical, dental, or hospital care shall terminate on or before the child's twenty
-
first birthday. The secretary of social services may promulgate reasonable and necessary rules pursuant to chapter
1-26
to implement this section.
Source:
SL 1970, ch 154; SL 1981, ch 199, § 43; SL 1990, ch 210; SDCL
28-7-3.1
; SL 1997, ch 166, § 23; SL 2004, ch 167, § 38.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_65">
            <akn:num>28-1-65</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Child support enforcement unit--Federal money--Enforcement powers</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-65
.
Child support enforcement unit--Federal money--Enforcement powers.
The Department of Social Services shall establish a child support enforcement unit and may, in accordance with chapter
4-8B
, apply for and receive federal funds under the provisions of Title IV-D of the Social Security Act. The department may also enforce the child support obligations for any child who is receiving temporary assistance for needy families or foster care maintenance payments under Title IV-E. The department shall enforce the spousal support obligation for a parent who is living with his or her child if the support obligation has been established for the parent by court order and the child support obligation is being enforced by the department.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 187, § 1; SL 1982, ch 208, § 1; SL 1986, ch 218, § 58; SDCL §
28-7-17.1
; SL 1997, ch 166, § 23; SL 2004, ch 167, § 39; SL 2019, ch 127, § 8.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_66">
            <akn:num>28-1-66</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Availability of child support enforcement services--Fees--Payment by responsible parent</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-66
.
Availability of child support enforcement services--Fees--Payment by responsible parent.
The Department of Social Services shall make child support enforcement services available to an individual not otherwise eligible for those purposes upon application from an individual and payment of a reasonable fee. The department shall promulgate rules pursuant to chapter
1-26
to set the application fee and any fees imposed for collection services. However, the application fee shall be refunded to the applicant by the parent responsible for paying child support payments and the fees imposed for collection services shall be paid by the parent responsible for paying child support payments to the Department of Social Services.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 187, § 2; SL 1982, ch 209, § 1; SL 1985, ch 226; SDCL 28-7-17.2; SL 1997, ch 166, § 23.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_67">
            <akn:num>28-1-67</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Clearing account for child support enforcement collections</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-67
.
Clearing account for child support enforcement collections.
The state treasurer, on behalf of the Department of Social Services, with the approval of the Bureau of Finance and Management, shall establish an account or system of accounts in the state treasury for the receipt and disbursement of child support enforcement collections. The department shall pay all moneys due to the federal government, county, or other local governmental units of South Dakota, or other state and local governmental units as well as all moneys due to private persons who are not recipients of aid under the South Dakota Title IV
-
a plan, and all other collections shall be remitted to the general fund on a quarterly basis, each remittance to be due thirty days after the end of each fiscal quarter.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 166; SL 1977, ch 224; SDCL
28-7-17.4
; SL 1997, ch 166, § 23.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_68">
            <akn:num>28-1-68</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Confidentiality of enforcement services applications and records</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_68__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>For inspection by persons authorized by this state or the United States in connection with their official duties;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_68__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>For the purpose of fair hearings provided by law.
Source:
SL 1977, ch 222; SL 1982, ch 208, § 2; SDCL 28-7-17.5; SL 1997, ch 166, § 23.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_69">
            <akn:num>28-1-69</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Information on amount owed sent to consumer reporting agencies--Consumer reporting agency defined--Notice to obligor</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-69
.
Information on amount owed sent to consumer reporting agencies--Consumer reporting agency defined--Notice to obligor.
The department shall furnish information regarding the amount of overdue support owed by an obligor to any consumer reporting agency, as defined by this section, upon the request of the agency, or as determined by the secretary. The term, consumer reporting agency, means any person who, for monetary fees, dues or on a cooperative nonprofit basis, regularly engages in whole or in part in the practice of assembling or evaluating consumer credit information or other information on consumers for the purpose of furnishing consumer reports to third parties, and who uses any means or facility of interstate commerce for the purpose of preparing or furnishing consumer reports. The department shall send the notice to the obligor regarding the proposed release of information and the procedures available to contest the accuracy of the information. The consumer reporting agency has no obligation to accept or use the information provided to it under this section.
Source:
SL 1986, ch 218, § 56; SL 1991, ch 226; SDCL
28-7-25
; SL 1997, ch 166, §§ 23, 54.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_70">
            <akn:num>28-1-70</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 153, §§ 4 to 7</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-70
to 28-1-73.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 153, §§ 4 to 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_74">
            <akn:num>28-1-74</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-74</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-74.
Repealed by SL 2011, ch 134, § 3.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_75">
            <akn:num>28-1-75</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 153, § 8</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-75
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 153, § 8.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_76">
            <akn:num>28-1-76</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-1-76</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-76.
Repealed by SL 2011, ch 134, § 5.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_77">
            <akn:num>28-1-77</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 153, § 9</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-77
.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 153, § 9.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_78">
            <akn:num>28-1-78</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Program of recoveries and fraud investigations--Debt collection and fraud allegation investigations--Authority of investigators</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_78__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Initiate and conduct any investigation if the program has cause to believe that a fraudulent act has been committed by a recipient of assistance from department programs;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_78__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Review any report or complaint of an alleged fraudulent act to determine whether such report requires further investigation and conduct such investigation;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_78__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Obtain access to any record related to residence, household composition, employment, finances and resources, and medical records as authorized by the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA), PL 104-199, as amended through January 1, 2005, to assist in investigation of an alleged fraudulent act and may require by administrative subpoena the production of any book, record, or other information; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_78__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Cooperate with federal, state, and local law enforcement, prosecuting attorneys, and the attorney general in the investigation and prosecution of any fraudulent act where public assistance has been granted or applied for under the welfare laws of this state.
Source:
SL 2005, ch 146, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_79">
            <akn:num>28-1-79</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Collection action to recover debts owed department</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-79
.
Collection action to recover debts owed department.
The program may take any collection action provided for in state and federal law and regulation to recover debts owed the department.
Source:
SL 2005, ch 146, § 2.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_80">
            <akn:num>28-1-80</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Confidentiality of investigative records and files of program</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-80
.
Confidentiality of investigative records and files of program.
All investigative records and files of the program established pursuant to §§
28-1-78
to
28-1-81
, inclusive, are confidential. No investigative record may be released except to department personnel, federal, state, and local law enforcement, prosecuting attorneys, and the attorney general in the investigation and prosecution of fraudulent acts. No investigative record or file may be released to any other person except pursuant to a court order. All collection files are confidential. No collection file may be released except in accordance with recipient confidentiality requirements of the department.
Source:
SL 2005, ch 146, § 3.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_81">
            <akn:num>28-1-81</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Report to Governor and Legislature concerning program activities</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-81
.
Report to Governor and Legislature concerning program activities.
The secretary of the Department of Social Services shall annually report to the Governor and the Legislature concerning the activities of the program including the number and type of cases investigated, the outcome of such investigations, and costs and expenditures incurred during such investigations.
Source:
SL 2005, ch 146, § 4.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_82">
            <akn:num>28-1-82</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Unauthorized supplemental nutrition assistance program benefits</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_82__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Acquires, purchases, possesses, or uses any Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program EBT card to obtain Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program benefits that the person is not entitled to;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_82__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Transfers, sells, trades, gives, or otherwise disposes of any Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program EBT card to another person not entitled to receive or use it in exchange for anything of value;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_82__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Acquires, purchases, possesses, or uses any eligible goods purchased with a Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program EBT card that the person is not entitled to; or</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_82__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Transfers, sells, trades, gives, or otherwise disposes of any eligible goods purchased with a Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program EBT card to another person not entitled to receive it in exchange for anything of value.
Source:
SL 2005, ch 148, § 1; SL 2023, ch 94, § 2.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_83">
            <akn:num>28-1-83</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Unauthorized supplemental nutrition assistance program benefits--Penalty</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_83__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>or</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_83__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>with a Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program EBT card value of one thousand dollars or less is guilty of a Class 1 misdemeanor. Any person convicted of an offense under subdivision
28-1-82</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_83__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>or</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_83__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>with a Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program EBT card value of more than one thousand dollars is guilty of a Class 6 felony. Amounts involved in the acquisition or transfer of EBT cards in violation of subdivisions
28-1-82</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_83__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_83__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>or</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_83__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>is guilty of a Class 1 misdemeanor.
Source:
SL 2005, ch 148, § 2; SL 2023, ch 94, § 3.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_84">
            <akn:num>28-1-84</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Unauthorized supplemental nutrition assistance program benefits--Definition</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-1-84
.
Unauthorized supplemental nutrition assistance program benefits--Definition.
As used in §§
28-1-82
to
28-1-84
, inclusive, the term, Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program EBT card, means any electronic benefit transfer card issued for the purchase of food pursuant to the Food Stamp Act of 1997, 7 U.S.C. §§ 2011 to 2029, inclusive, in effect on January 1, 2005.
Source:
SL 2005, ch 148, § 3; SL 2023, ch 94, § 4.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_1_85">
            <akn:num>28-1-85</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Refugee resettlement agencies--Required annual report</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_85__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>A detailed description of each program, service, or resource provided by the agency in support of refugee resettlement;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_85__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The number of resettled refugees who were provided with programs, services, or other resources in each political subdivision; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_85__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Demographic information pertaining to the resettled refugees who were provided with programs, services, or other resources, including:</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_85__subsec_3__para_a">
                <akn:num>(a)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Age;</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_85__subsec_3__para_b">
                <akn:num>(b)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Country of origin;</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_85__subsec_3__para_c">
                <akn:num>(c)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Education; and</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_1_85__subsec_3__para_d">
                <akn:num>(d)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Gender.
The report must also include the number of refugees that the entity anticipates will arrive and receive resettlement services by or through the agency during the current fiscal year.
Source:
SL 2025, ch 111, § 1.</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_10">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-10</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Food Stamp Program</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_1">
            <akn:num>28-10-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Definition of terms</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Director," the director of service to the blind and visually impaired;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Division," the Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Impediment to employment," a physical or mental condition which constitutes, contributes to or if not corrected will probably result in an obstruction to independent living or occupational performance;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Individual with a visual disability," any person who has a visual impairment which results in a substantial impediment to employment or independent living and who can benefit in terms of an employment or independent living outcome;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Maintenance," money payments not exceeding the estimated cost of subsistence during vocational rehabilitation;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Occupational licenses," any license, permit, or other written authority required by any governmental unit to be obtained in order to engage in an occupation;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Physical restoration," any medical, surgical, or therapeutic treatment necessary to correct or substantially reduce an impediment to employment of an individual with a visual disability within a reasonable length of time including medical, psychiatric, dental and surgical treatment, nursing services, hospital care, drugs, medical and surgical supplies, and prosthetic appliances, but excluding curative treatment for acute or transitory conditions;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Prosthetic appliance," any artificial device necessary to support or take the place of a part of the body or to increase the acuity of a sense organ;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_9">
              <akn:num>(9)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Rehabilitation training," all necessary training provided to a person with a visual disability to compensate for an impediment to employment including manual, preconditioning, pre
-
vocational, vocational, and supplementary training and training provided for the purpose of achieving broader and more remunerative skills and capacities;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_10">
              <akn:num>(10)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Service," all of the services provided by the Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired, including independent living, rehabilitation, and minor medical services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_1__subsec_11">
              <akn:num>(11)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Vocational rehabilitation" and "vocational rehabilitation services," any services found by the director to be necessary to enable an individual with a visual disability to engage in a remunerative occupation including assessment for determining eligibility and vocational rehabilitation needs, counseling and placement, rehabilitation training, physical restoration, transportation, occupational licenses, customary occupational tools, equipment, maintenance, training books, and materials and adaptive rehabilitation technology devices and services.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 1; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B01; SL 1969, ch 215, §§ 1, 2; SL 1977, ch 226, § 15; SL 1994, ch 231, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_2">
            <akn:num>28-10-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-2</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-2.
Repealed by SL 1977, ch 226, § 26</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_2_1">
            <akn:num>28-10-2.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Division created</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-2.1
.
Division created.
There is hereby created a division for the purpose of rehabilitation of and services to individuals with visual disabilities to be known as the "Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired."
Source:
SL 1973, ch 2, § 74; SL 1977, ch 226, § 16; SL 1994, ch 231, § 2.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_3">
            <akn:num>28-10-3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-3</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-3.
Repealed by SL 1977, ch 226, § 26</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_4">
            <akn:num>28-10-4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-4</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-4.
Superseded</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_5">
            <akn:num>28-10-5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Subordinate administrative units within division</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-5
.
Subordinate administrative units within division.
The director of service to the blind and visually impaired shall establish appropriate subordinate administrative units within the Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B03 (2); SL 1977, ch 226, § 17.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_6">
            <akn:num>28-10-6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Employment of personnel for division</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-6
.
Employment of personnel for division.
The director of service to the blind and visually impaired shall employ, pursuant to chapter
3-6D
, personnel as the director deems necessary for the efficient performance of the Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired.
Source:
SL 1943, ch 267, § 3; SL 1945, ch 308, § 3; SL 1947, ch 248, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B03 (3); SL 1977, ch 226, § 18; SL 2018, ch 12, § 11.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_7">
            <akn:num>28-10-7</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Political activity by vocational rehabilitation employees prohibited--Discharge or suspension for violation</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-7
.
Political activity by vocational rehabilitation employees prohibited--Discharge or suspension for violation.
No officer or employee engaged in the administration of the vocational rehabilitation program shall take any active part in the management of political campaigns or participate in any political activity, except that he shall retain the right to vote as he may please and to express his opinion as a citizen on all subjects. Any officer or employee violating this provision shall be subject to discharge or suspension.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 12; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B12.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_8">
            <akn:num>28-10-8</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Delegation of powers by director--Powers not subject to delegation</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-8
.
Delegation of powers by director--Powers not subject to delegation.
The director of service to the blind and visually impaired may delegate to any officer or employee of the Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired such of his powers and duties, except the making of the division's rules, as may be necessary or appropriate.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B03 (8); SL 1977, ch 226, § 19.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_9">
            <akn:num>28-10-9</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-9</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-9.
Repealed by SL 1994, ch 231, § 3</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_10">
            <akn:num>28-10-10</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Vocational rehabilitation services provided to eligible persons</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-10
.
Vocational rehabilitation services provided to eligible persons.
The Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired shall provide vocational rehabilitation services to individuals with visual disabilities determined by the director to be eligible.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 4; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B04; SL 1977, ch 226, § 20; SL 1994, ch 231, § 4.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_11">
            <akn:num>28-10-11</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Rehabilitation services provided based on economic need</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_11__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Physical restoration;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_11__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Transportation not provided to determine the eligibility of the individual for vocational rehabilitation services and the nature and extent of the services necessary;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_11__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Occupational licenses;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_11__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Customary occupational tools and equipment, excluding computer-related assistive technology devices needed to overcome visual disability as an impediment to employment for competitive employment purposes;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_11__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Maintenance;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_11__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Training books and materials; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_11__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Tuition and fees for participating in postsecondary academic training programs under the Federal Student Financial Assistance Program.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 7; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B07; SL 1969, ch 215, § 5; SL 1976, ch 172, § 4; SL 1990, ch 212; SL 1994, ch 231, § 5; SL 2001, ch 153, § 2; SL 2012, ch 14, § 5.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_12">
            <akn:num>28-10-12</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-12</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-12.
Repealed by SL 1994, ch 231, § 6</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_13">
            <akn:num>28-10-13</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Certification of funds for disbursement</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-13
.
Certification of funds for disbursement.
In carrying out his duties under this chapter, the director of service to the blind and visually impaired shall make certification for disbursement, in accordance with regulations, of funds available for services including vocational rehabilitation.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B03 (5).</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_14">
            <akn:num>28-10-14</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Review of determinations of counselor or coordinator--Written final determination by division director required</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-14
.
Review of determinations of counselor or coordinator--Written final determination by division director required.
The director shall establish procedures, pursuant to chapter
1-26
, for the review of determinations made by a rehabilitation counselor or coordinator upon the request of the individual with a visual disability, or the individual's parents or guardians. The procedures shall include a requirement that the final decision concerning the review of a determination be made in writing by the division director. The division director may not delegate responsibility to make a final decision to any other employee of the division.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 9; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B09; SL 1977, ch 226, § 21; SL 1981, ch 218, § 2; SL 1989, ch 21, § 148; SL 1994, ch 231, § 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_15">
            <akn:num>28-10-15</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-15</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-15.
Repealed by SL 1994, ch 231, § 8</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_16">
            <akn:num>28-10-16</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Unauthorized use of records and lists as misdemeanor--Dismissal</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-16
.
Unauthorized use of records and lists as misdemeanor--Dismissal.
It shall be a Class 1 misdemeanor and subject the violator to dismissal, except for purposes directly connected with the administration of the vocational rehabilitation program, and in accordance with regulations, for any person or persons to solicit, disclose, receive, or make use of, or authorize, knowingly permit, participate in, or acquiesce in the use of any list of, or names of, or any information concerning, persons applying for or receiving vocational rehabilitation, directly or indirectly derived from the records, papers, files, or communications of the state or subdivisions or agencies thereof, or acquired in the course of the performance of official duties.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 10; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B10.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_17">
            <akn:num>28-10-17</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-17</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-17.
Repealed by SL 1994, ch 231, § 9</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_18">
            <akn:num>28-10-18</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Cooperation with public and private agencies in rehabilitation studies and programs</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-18
.
Cooperation with public and private agencies in rehabilitation studies and programs.
In carrying out the purposes of this chapter, the Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired may cooperate with other departments, agencies, and institutions, both public and private, in providing for the vocational rehabilitation of persons with visual disabilities in studying the problems and in establishing, developing and providing, in conformity with the purposes of this chapter, such programs, facilities and services as may be necessary or desirable.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 4; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B04 (1); SL 1994, ch 231, § 10.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_19">
            <akn:num>28-10-19</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-19</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-19.
Repealed by SL 1994, ch 231, § 11</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_20">
            <akn:num>28-10-20</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Reciprocal agreements with other states for vocational rehabilitation</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-20
.
Reciprocal agreements with other states for vocational rehabilitation.
In carrying out the purposes of this chapter, the Division of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired is authorized among other things to enter into reciprocal agreements with other states to provide for the vocational rehabilitation of residents of the states concerned to the extent of services rendered by the State of South Dakota.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 4; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B04 (2).</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_21">
            <akn:num>28-10-21</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Procedural regulations made by secretary</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The protection of records and confidential information;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Application requirements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Eligibility requirements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Income and resource requirements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Administration and operation of vocational rehabilitation and independent living programs;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Grant applications and awards;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Administrative reviews and fair hearings;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Amount, scope, and duration of rehabilitative services and independent living services; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_10_21__subsec_9">
              <akn:num>(9)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Fees.
Source:
SL 1947, ch 248, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.39B03</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_22">
            <akn:num>28-10-22</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-22</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-22.
Repealed by SL 1982, ch 16, § 23</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_23">
            <akn:num>28-10-23</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-23, 28-10-24</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-23, 28-10-24.
Repealed by SL 1977, ch 226, § 26</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_25">
            <akn:num>28-10-25</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Board of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired created</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-25
.
Board of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired created.
There is hereby created a Board of Service to the Blind and Visually Impaired.
Source:
SL 1990, ch 213, § 1; SL 1993, ch 20, § 2; SL 2001, ch 155, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_10_26">
            <akn:num>28-10-26</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-10-26</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-10-26.
Repealed by SL 2001, ch 155 § 2</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_11">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-11</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Child Support Enforcement</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_11_1">
            <akn:num>28-11-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Department to enter agreement with federal government and make disability determinations</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-11-1
.
Department to enter agreement with federal government and make disability determinations.
The Department of Human Services, through the Division of Rehabilitation Services, may enter into an agreement on behalf of the state with the secretary of health and human services to carry out the provisions of the federal Social Security Act, as amended or superseded as of January 1, 1978, relating to the making of determinations of disability.
Source:
SL 1955, ch 261, § 1; SDC Supp 1960, § 55.1111; SL 1977, ch 226, § 25; SL 1978, ch 212; SL 1989, ch 21, § 149.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_11_2">
            <akn:num>28-11-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-11-2</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-11-2.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, § 15</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_12">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-12</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Child Care Facilities</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_12_1">
            <akn:num>28-12-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Agreement with federal government--Purpose--Promulgation of rules</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-12-1
.
Agreement with federal government--Purpose--Promulgation of rules.
The Department of Social Services may enter into agreements and contracts with the federal government and its agencies and with the political subdivisions of this state for the purpose of participating in the Food Stamp Act of 1964 (P.L. 88-525) and any related acts, as amended to January 1, 2004. The secretary of social services shall promulgate rules, pursuant to chapter
1-26
, as required by the federal government for the administration of the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program in this state. The rules must be in accordance with federal regulations implementing the Food Stamp Act of 1964, as amended to January 1, 2004.
Source:
SL 1967, ch 269; SL 1981, ch 199, § 54; SL 2004, ch 167, § 65; SL 2023, ch 94, § 5.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_12_2">
            <akn:num>28-12-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Agreements between political subdivisions and division authorized</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-12-2
.
Agreements between political subdivisions and division authorized.
The political subdivisions of this state are hereby authorized to enter into agreements and contracts with the Department of Social Services for the purposes set forth in this chapter.
Source:
SL 1967, ch 269.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_12_3">
            <akn:num>28-12-3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Certain drug offenders exempted from federal eligibility sanctions</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_12_3__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>of Public Law 104-193.
Source:
SL 2009, ch 141, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_12_4">
            <akn:num>28-12-4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Child support cooperation as condition of eligibility</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-12-4
.
Child support cooperation as condition of eligibility.
The Department of Social Services shall require each person to cooperate with the Division of Child Support as a condition of eligibility, pursuant to 7 C.F.R. § 273.11(o).
Source:
SL 2017, ch 121, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_13">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-13</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Community Action Agencies</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>County duty to relieve poor persons--Taxation--Determination of eligibility</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-1
.
County duty to relieve poor persons--Taxation--Determination of eligibility.
Every county shall relieve and support all poor and indigent persons who have established residency therein, as that term is defined in §§
28-13-2
to
28-13-16.2
, inclusive, and who have made application to the county, whenever they shall stand in need. Each board of county commissioners may raise money by taxation for the support and employment of the poor. If a person is receiving benefits from the Department of Social Services, the board of county commissioners may determine if he is eligible for county relief.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0101; SL 1939, ch 200, § 1; SL 1941, ch 211, § 1; SL 1976, ch 173, § 1; SL 1980, ch 202, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_1_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-1.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>"Indigent or poor person" defined--Eligibility standards</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-1.1
.
"Indigent or poor person" defined--Eligibility standards.
For the purposes of this chapter, an indigent or poor person is any person who does not have sufficient money, credit, or property to be self
-
supporting; who has no one to look to who is legally required to provide support; or who is unable to be self
-
supporting through work because of illness or injury. In applying this definition, each county shall establish reasonable eligibility standards for county poor relief.
Source:
SL 1984, ch 203, § 1; SL 1997, ch 170, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_1_2">
            <akn:num>28-13-1.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Considerations in establishing eligibility standards</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-1.2
.
Considerations in establishing eligibility standards.
A county in establishing eligibility standards for county poor relief shall take into consideration an applicant's total economic resources including current assets and income, sources of financial support to which the applicant is legally entitled and total economic needs. In a case involving support among family members the county shall take into consideration family size, total family economic resources, and total family economic needs.
Source:
SL 1984, ch 203, § 2.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_1_3">
            <akn:num>28-13-1.3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Medically indigent person defined</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_3__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Requires medically necessary hospital services for which no public or private third
-
party coverage, such as insurance, veterans' assistance, medicaid, or medicare, is available which covers the actual cost of hospitalization;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_3__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Has no ability or only limited ability, as determined under the provisions of this chapter, to pay a debt for hospitalization;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_3__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Has not voluntarily reduced or eliminated ownership or control of an asset for the purpose of establishing eligibility;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_3__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Is not indigent by design; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_3__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Is not a veteran or a member of a Native American tribe who is eligible or would have been eligible for services through the veterans administration or the Indian Health Service if the services had been applied for within seventy
-
two hours of the person's admission.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 4.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_1_4">
            <akn:num>28-13-1.4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Appeal regarding medical indigence</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_4__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>In violation of constitutional or statutory provisions;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_4__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>In excess of the statutory authority of the county;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_4__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Made upon unlawful procedure;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_4__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Affected by other error of law;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_4__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Clearly erroneous in light of the entire evidence in the record; or</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_1_4__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Clearly unwarranted exercise of discretion.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 29.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_2">
            <akn:num>28-13-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Residency acquired for poor relief purposes</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-2
.
Residency acquired for poor relief purposes.
A person may establish a residency in any county so as to oblige such county to relieve and support him, in case he is poor and stands in need of relief, as provided by §§
28-13-3
to
28-13-16.2
, inclusive.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0102; SL 1976, ch 173, § 2.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_3">
            <akn:num>28-13-3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Residency required for assistance--Establishment</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-3
.
Residency required for assistance--Establishment.
Except as otherwise provided in this chapter, any person, in order to be entitled to assistance, shall have an established residency in the state, and in the county where the application is made. The residency shall be established by his personal presence, in a fixed and permanent abode and his intention to remain there. In determining the residency of an applicant the county commissioners may consider the establishment of a local bank account by the applicant, the applicant's driver's license address, an automobile registration, the enrollment of applicant's children in a local school, and the applicant's voter registration; however, the absence of any of the above considerations shall not be a positive determination of nonresidency.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0102 (4); SL 1976, ch 173, § 3; SL 1980, ch 202, § 2.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_4">
            <akn:num>28-13-4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-4</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-4.
Repealed by SL 1976, ch 173, § 35</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_5">
            <akn:num>28-13-5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Children's residency</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-5
.
Children's residency.
For the purposes of this chapter, children shall have the same residency as their parents, the party granted their legal custody pursuant to court order or decree, or as fixed by their guardian.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0102 (2); SL 1976, ch 173, § 6.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_6">
            <akn:num>28-13-6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-6, 28-13-7</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-6, 28-13-7.
Repealed by SL 1976, ch 173, § 35</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_8">
            <akn:num>28-13-8</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Residency continued until lost by new residency</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-8
.
Residency continued until lost by new residency.
For the purposes of this chapter a person's residency, when once legally established, shall continue until it is lost by establishing residency in another state or county.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0102 (6); SL 1941, ch 211, § 2; SL 1957, ch 263; SL 1961, ch 261; SL 1976, ch 173, § 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_9">
            <akn:num>28-13-9</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-9 to 28-13-11</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-9 to 28-13-11.
Repealed by SL 1972, ch 158, § 1</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_12">
            <akn:num>28-13-12</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Residency not established by state acceptance of application</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-12
.
Residency not established by state acceptance of application.
The acceptance of an applicant for any type of public assistance administered by the Department of Social Services, in a county where the applicant has not established residency in accordance with §
28-13-3
, shall not operate to establish a residency for the purposes of this chapter in that county.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 254, § 1; SDC Supp 1960, § 50.0102-1; SL 1976, ch 173, § 8.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_13">
            <akn:num>28-13-13</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-13</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-13.
Repealed by SL 1976, ch 173, § 35</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_14">
            <akn:num>28-13-14</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Residency not established by residence in health care facility</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-14
.
Residency not established by residence in health care facility.
An occupant or patient of any health care facility, licensed pursuant to the provisions of chapter
34-12
, who has not otherwise established residency in accordance with §
28-13-3
in the county where such facility is situated, shall not establish residency in such county solely by virtue of becoming and remaining an occupant or patient of such facility.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 254, § 2; SDC Supp 1960, § 50.0102-1; SL 1972, ch 158, § 2; SL 1976, ch 173, § 9.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_15">
            <akn:num>28-13-15</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-15</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-15.
Repealed by SL 1976, ch 173, § 35</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_16">
            <akn:num>28-13-16</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>County commissioners to have responsibility for care and relief of poor persons</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-16
.
County commissioners to have responsibility for care and relief of poor persons.
The county commissioners in each county are responsible for the care and relief of all poor persons in the county as provided by this chapter as long as those persons remain eligible. The commissioners may designate a county official to assist in the coordination of poor relief information with other counties.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0201; SL 1980, ch 202, § 3; SL 1986, ch 234; SL 1997, ch 170, § 2.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_16_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-16.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Waiting period imposed at board's discretion while residency investigated</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-16.1
.
Waiting period imposed at board's discretion while residency investigated.
The board of county commissioners may, except for their obligations under §§
28-13-37
and
28-13-38
, impose upon applicants for assistance such a reasonable waiting period as they may determine to be necessary in order to adequately investigate and consider all factors relevant to determining whether an applicant has established residency in good faith in the state, and in the county where the application is made.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 173, § 4.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_16_2">
            <akn:num>28-13-16.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Intentional fraud or deceit to receive assistance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-16.2
.
Intentional fraud or deceit to receive assistance.
Any applicant for assistance who knowingly makes any false statement, with intent to defraud, as to his financial status or other required information, or in any way intentionally deceives any county commissioner, or any welfare worker employed pursuant to §
28-13-22
, in order to receive assistance, shall be guilty of a Class 1 misdemeanor.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 173, § 5.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_17">
            <akn:num>28-13-17</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Proceedings by and against commissioners in name of county</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-17
.
Proceedings by and against commissioners in name of county.
In all actions or proceedings in favor of or against any such commissioners, pertaining to or connected with the poor of their respective counties, the same shall be conducted in favor of or against such county in its corporate name.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0206.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_18">
            <akn:num>28-13-18</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Record of poor relief payments available in investigation of residency</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-18
.
Record of poor relief payments available in investigation of residency.
For the purpose of aiding the investigation of an applicant's residency conducted pursuant to §
28-13-3
, each county auditor shall make the information recorded pursuant to §
28-14-7
available upon request to any county commissioner, county auditor, or welfare worker employed pursuant to §
28-13-22
.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 173, § 10.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_19">
            <akn:num>28-13-19</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Establishment of special emergency county welfare account--Purpose--Deposit and withdrawal of fund--Source of fund</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-19
.
Establishment of special emergency county welfare account--Purpose--Deposit and withdrawal of fund--Source of fund.
The board of county commissioners may establish a special emergency county welfare account upon which the county welfare departments may make immediate, direct cash withdrawals up to one hundred dollars a month to meet special emergency requirements of said county welfare departments.
The special account shall be deposited with a local bank and subject to withdrawals upon the signatures of county officials designated and authorized to do the same by the board of county commissioners. The board shall from time to time appropriate money from the general fund to this special account.
Source:
SL 1966, ch 32; SL 1985, ch 77, § 16.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_20">
            <akn:num>28-13-20</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Services required of applicant--Contract for repayment of assistance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-20
.
Services required of applicant--Contract for repayment of assistance.
Whenever financial assistance is requested under the provisions of this chapter, the board of county commissioners may require the applicant to perform labor or other services of a public nature commensurate with the amount of aid desired or granted. In addition, the board may require the recipient of assistance to enter into a contract for the repayment of all or part of the assistance he receives.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0202; SL 1976, ch 173, § 11; SL 1982, ch 213, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_20_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-20.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Regular county employees not replaced by poor relief applicants--Maximum hours of work</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-20.1
.
Regular county employees not replaced by poor relief applicants--Maximum hours of work.
No person required to perform labor or other services under §
28-13-20
shall be used to replace any regular employee of the county. No such person shall be required to work more than eight hours in a day nor more than forty hours in a week.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 173, § 12.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_20_2">
            <akn:num>28-13-20.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Refusal to work without just cause--Eligibility for assistance terminated</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-20.2
.
Refusal to work without just cause--Eligibility for assistance terminated.
Any person who without just cause refuses to report for work to which he has been assigned by the board of county commissioners, or by a welfare worker employed pursuant to §
28-13-22
, shall thereupon become ineligible for further assistance under this chapter until such work is commenced.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 173, § 13.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_21">
            <akn:num>28-13-21</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>County funds expended on federal work relief projects--Agreements with federal agencies--Construction of public buildings not authorized</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-21
.
County funds expended on federal work relief projects--Agreements with federal agencies--Construction of public buildings not authorized.
Every county may expend moneys raised by taxation for the support and employment of the poor for the purpose of sponsoring federal work projects now, or hereafter, established by work relief agencies of the United States, whether now existing or hereafter established by the United States, for the purpose of providing support and employment for poor and indigent persons and may enter into agreements therefor with such federal agencies. The provisions of this section shall not authorize the construction of public buildings or additions thereto in conjunction with federal agencies.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0101 as added by SL 1939, ch 200, § 1; SL 1939, ch 200, § 2; SL 1941, ch 211, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_22">
            <akn:num>28-13-22</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Employment of welfare workers to distribute funds and supplies to poor</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-22
.
Employment of welfare workers to distribute funds and supplies to poor.
Whenever the board of county commissioners, in any county having within its borders a municipal corporation of the first class, deems it necessary and advisable for the best interests of the county, for the protection of health or the promotion of morals and order within the county, to employ one or more persons to act as welfare workers in the distribution of funds or supplies to needy poor within the county, derived from any source, such board of county commissioners shall be empowered to employ such welfare workers.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 12.1602.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_23">
            <akn:num>28-13-23</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Annual allowances to competent poor persons</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-23
.
Annual allowances to competent poor persons.
The board of county commissioners may in its discretion allow and pay to poor persons who may become county charges and who are of mature years and sound mind, and who from their general character will probably be benefited thereby, and also to the parents of children with intellectual disabilities and children otherwise helpless and requiring the attention of their parents, and who are unable to provide for such children themselves, such annual allowance as will not exceed the charge of their maintenance in the ordinary mode, such board taking the usual amount of charges in like cases as the rule for making such allowance.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0205; SL 2013, ch 125, § 15.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_24">
            <akn:num>28-13-24</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-24</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-24.
Repealed by SL 1972, ch 43, § 5</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_25">
            <akn:num>28-13-25</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-25</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-25.
Repealed by SL 1976, ch 173, § 35</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_26">
            <akn:num>28-13-26</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Employment of physician to attend poor persons in county--Annual salary--Monthly report by physician</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-26
.
Employment of physician to attend poor persons in county--Annual salary--Monthly report by physician.
Each board of county commissioners may annually employ a duly qualified physician and surgeon registered and licensed in the healing arts, as the term "healing arts" is defined by chapter
36-2
, as county physician, whose duty it shall be to attend and render his services as physician and surgeon to poor persons of the county. The board of county commissioners shall fix the annual salary to be paid and which shall be paid monthly with warrants of the county auditor upon proper verified vouchers approved by the county commissioners. It shall be the duty of such physician and surgeon to file with the county auditor not later than the first day of each month a report disclosing the patients treated by him, the value and kind of services rendered and the name and address of the person so treated within the previous thirty days.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 31; SDC Supp 1960, § 50.0204-1; SL 1976, ch 173, § 14.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_27">
            <akn:num>28-13-27</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Hospitalization of poor persons--Definition of terms</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Actual cost of hospitalization," the actual cost to a hospital of providing hospital services to a medically indigent person, determined by applying the ratios of costs to charges appearing on the statement of costs required in §
28-13-28
to charges at the hospital in effect at the time the hospital services are provided;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Emergency hospital services," treatment in the most appropriate hospital available to meet the emergency need. The physician, physician assistant, or certified nurse practitioner on duty or on call at the hospital must determine whether the individual requires emergency hospital care. The need for emergency hospital care is established if the absence of emergency care is expected to result in death, additional serious jeopardy to the individual's health, serious impairment to the individual's bodily functions, or serious dysfunction of any bodily organ or part. The term does not include care for which treatment is available and routinely provided in a clinic or physician's office;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Hospital," any hospital licensed as such by the state in which it is located;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Household," the patient, minor children of the patient living with the patient, and anyone else living with the patient to whom the patient has the legal right to look for support;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Nonemergency care," hospitalization which is medically necessary and recommended by a physician licensed under chapter
36-4
but does not require immediate care or attention;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Indigent by design," an individual who meets any one of the following criteria:</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_6__para_a">
                <akn:num>(a)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Is able to work but has chosen not to work;</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_6__para_b">
                <akn:num>(b)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Is a student at a postsecondary institution who has chosen not to purchase health insurance;</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_6__para_c">
                <akn:num>(c)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Has failed to purchase or elect major medical health insurance or health benefits made available through an employer-based health benefit plan although the person was financially able, pursuant to §
28-13-32.11
, to purchase or elect the insurance or health benefits;</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_6__para_d">
                <akn:num>(d)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Has failed to purchase available major medical health insurance although the individual was insurable and was financially able, pursuant to §
28-13-32.11
, to purchase the insurance. For purposes of this subdivision, an individual is presumed insurable unless the individual can produce sufficient evidence to show that the individual was declined major medical insurance by an insurance company and the individual did not qualify for any guarantees of major medical insurance available through any legal or contractual right that was not exercised; or</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
              <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27__subsec_6__para_e">
                <akn:num>(e)</akn:num>
                <akn:content>
                  <akn:p>Has transferred resources for purposes of establishing eligibility for medical assistance available under the provisions of this chapter. The lookback period for making this determination includes the thirty-six month period immediately prior to the onset of the individual's illness and continues through the period of time for which the individual is requesting services.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 1; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B01; SL 1980, ch 202, § 4; SL 1984, ch 203, § 3; SL 1988, ch 225, § 1; SL 1991, ch 227, § 1; SL 1997, ch 170, § 3; SL 2000, ch 134, § 1; SL 2017, ch 171, § 50.</akn:p>
                </akn:content>
              </akn:subsection>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_27_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-27.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Medically necessary hospital services</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27_1__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Are consistent with the person's symptoms, diagnosis, condition, or injury;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27_1__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Are recognized as the prevailing standard and are consistent with generally accepted professional medical standards of the provider's peer group;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27_1__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Are provided in response to a life
-
threatening condition; to treat pain, injury, illness, or infection; to treat a condition which would result in physical or mental disability; or to achieve a level of physical or mental function consistent with prevailing standards for the diagnosis or condition;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27_1__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Are not furnished primarily for the convenience of the person or the provider; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_27_1__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>There is no other equally effective course of treatment available or suitable for the person needing the services which is more conservative or substantially less costly.
A county shall rely on the attending physician's determination as to medical necessity of hospital services unless evidence exists to the contrary.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 5.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_27_2">
            <akn:num>28-13-27.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Cost guidelines for medical and remedial services</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-27.2
.
Cost guidelines for medical and remedial services.
Except for the costs of emergency hospital services, a county may adopt guidelines which define the amount, scope, and duration of medical and remedial services available to eligible persons and the basis for and extent of payments made to providers by counties on behalf of eligible persons.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 6.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_28">
            <akn:num>28-13-28</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Statement of costs required of hospital caring for indigent persons--Frequency of statements</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-28
.
Statement of costs required of hospital caring for indigent persons--Frequency of statements.
A hospital may avail itself of the provisions of this chapter for purposes of determining payment for hospitalization of a medically indigent person only if the hospital has filed a detailed statement of costs with the secretary of social services in the form prescribed by the secretary. The statement of costs shall compute and set forth the ratios of costs to charges for the hospital's fiscal year covered by the statement of costs. The statement of costs shall be filed with the secretary at least annually, unless such period is extended or otherwise provided by the secretary, but a hospital may file a detailed statement of costs or amendments to such a statement once every six months.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 2; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B02; SL 1976, ch 173, § 15; SL 1991, ch 227, § 2; SL 1997, ch 170, § 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_29">
            <akn:num>28-13-29</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Cost governed by statement or amendment--Claim against county not to exceed usual hospital rates</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_29__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>or an amount established by the secretary of the Department of Social Services, whichever is less. The amount established by the secretary shall be based on medicaid payment methodology. A hospital may not maintain a claim against a county for any amount which exceeds the usual ordinary and reasonable charge for any hospital service, even if the charge is less than the hospital's actual cost of hospitalization. If the hospital furnishes hospital services to medically indigent persons residing in the county in which the hospital is located at rates less than the rates provided for in this section, the hospital shall furnish such hospital services to all medically indigent persons at the same rates.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 2; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B02; SL 1991, ch 227, § 3; SL 1997, ch 170, § 8.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_30">
            <akn:num>28-13-30</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Approval of statement by secretary--Modification of items in statement</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-30
.
Approval of statement by secretary--Modification of items in statement.
The secretary of social services shall make such investigation as necessary, and shall approve the statement of costs only if the statement is accurate, complete, and reliable as could reasonably be expected, and that it discloses, as nearly as may be reasonably determined, the ratios of costs to charges for the hospital's fiscal year covered by the statement of costs. In granting approval, the secretary may modify any items in the statement which require such modification and shall provide written notice of any such modification to the respective hospital.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 2; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B02; SL 1976, ch 173, § 16; SL 1991, ch 227, § 4; SL 1997, ch 170, § 23.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_31">
            <akn:num>28-13-31</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Continuation of statement in effect until withdrawn or amended--Effective date of amendments--Statements available for inspection</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-31
.
Continuation of statement in effect until withdrawn or amended--Effective date of amendments--Statements available for inspection.
No statement of costs, or amendment thereto, may take effect until approved by the secretary of social services and the expiration of thirty days from the filing thereof, and thereafter, for purposes of this chapter, shall remain in full force and effect until the next statement of costs, or amendment thereto, filed by the hospital pursuant to §
28-13-28
is approved by the secretary. Any such statement of costs, or amendments thereto, shall be a public record and be available for inspection at any time in behalf of any board of county commissioners.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 2; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B02; SL 1976, ch 173, § 17; SL 1991, ch 227, § 5; SL 1997, ch 170, § 24.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32">
            <akn:num>28-13-32</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>County commissioners' objections to statements</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-32
.
County commissioners' objections to statements.
Any board of county commissioners may at any time file, with the secretary of social services and the hospital concerned, objections in writing to any such statement of costs, any items therein, or amended thereto, which objections shall be passed upon by the secretary.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 2; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B02; SL 1976, ch 173, § 18; SL 1991, ch 227, § 6; SL 1997, ch 170, § 25.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-32</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-32.1, 28-13-32.2.
Repealed by SL 1988, ch 226, §§ 5, 6</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_3">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Medical indigency required for poor relief assistance in the event of hospitalization--Application required--Time--Limitation</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-32.3
.
Medical indigency required for poor relief assistance in the event of hospitalization--Application required--Time--Limitation.
To receive assistance under this chapter for the costs of hospitalization, a person must be medically indigent as defined in §
28-13-1.3
. The person or someone acting on behalf of the person shall apply to the person's county of residence for assistance within two years of the date of the hospital's discharge of the person.
Source:
SL 1988, ch 226, § 3; SL 1997, ch 170, § 9; SL 2002, ch 137, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_4">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Submission of application by hospital within one year of discharge--Contents--Additional information not to be required</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_4__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The notice of hospitalization as provided in §
28-13-34.1
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_4__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The dates of hospitalization;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_4__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The final diagnosis;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_4__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The cost of hospital services; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_4__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Any financial information in the possession of the hospital concerning the patient or the responsible party, including the availability of insurance coverage.
The county may not require the hospital to provide more information concerning such a medically indigent person than is contained in the application provided for in this section and the release of information provided for in §
28-13-34.2
.
Source:
SL 1988, ch 226, § 4; SL 1997, ch 170, § 10.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_5">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Determining medical indigence--Annual income guideline</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_5__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Using the housing index established in §
28-13-32.6
, determine the housing index for the person's county of residence. Multiply the county index by three hundred six dollars, the median gross rent of residences in South Dakota in 1996;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_5__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Using the federal poverty guidelines adopted in rules promulgated by the Department of Social Services pursuant to chapter
1-26
, determine the federal poverty level for the household size and multiply that figure by one hundred seventy
-
five percent; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_5__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Add the results of subdivisions</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_5__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_5__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>of this section and multiply by twelve.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 12; SL 1998, ch 165, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_6">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Housing indexes by county</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-32.6
.
Housing indexes by county.
The housing index for each county is as follows:
COUNTY
HOUSING INDEX
Aurora
0.65
Beadle
0.91
Bennett
0.86
Bon Homme
0.71
Brookings
0.96
Brown
0.95
Brule
0.80
Buffalo
0.77
Butte
0.91
Campbell
0.74
Charles Mix
0.65
Clark
0.72
Clay
0.95
Codington
0.92
Corson
0.47
Custer
1.03
Davison
0.90
Day
0.78
Deuel
0.79
Dewey
0.89
Douglas
0.69
Edmunds
0.71
Fall River
0.89
Faulk
0.66
Grant
0.81
Gregory
0.68
Haakon
0.80
Hamlin
0.70
Hand
0.70
Hanson
0.96
Harding
0.70
Hughes
1.03
Hutchinson
0.72
Hyde
0.75
Jackson
0.84
Jerauld
0.61
Jones
0.76
Kingsbury
0.67
Lake
0.78
Lawrence
1.00
Lincoln
0.93
Lyman
0.77
Marshall
0.72
McCook
0.73
McPherson
0.58
Meade
1.03
Mellette
0.74
Miner
0.65
Minnehaha
1.23
Moody
0.79
Oglala Lakota
0.81
Pennington
1.26
Perkins
0.65
Potter
0.86
Roberts
0.70
Sanborn
0.67
Spink
0.82
Stanley
1.06
Sully
0.82
Todd
0.79
Tripp
0.83
Turner
0.78
Union
0.87
Walworth
0.97
Yankton
0.93
Ziebach
0.82
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 13; SL 2015, ch 56 (HJR 1005), eff. May 1, 2015.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_7">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.7</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Determining household income--Sources</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Compensation paid to household members for personal services, whether designated as gross salary, wages, commissions, bonus, or otherwise;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Net income from self-employment, including profit or loss from a business, farm, or profession;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Income from seasonal employment;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Periodic payments from pensions or retirement programs, including social security, veterans' benefits, disability payments, and insurance contracts;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Income from annuities or trusts, except for a trust held by a third party for the benefit of the minor children of the household;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Interest, dividends, rents, royalties, or other gain derived from investments or capital assets;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Gain or loss from the sale, trade, or conversion of capital assets;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Reemployment assistance or unemployment insurance benefits and strike benefits;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_9">
              <akn:num>(9)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Workers' compensation benefits and settlements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_10">
              <akn:num>(10)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Alimony and child support payments received; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_7__subsec_11">
              <akn:num>(11)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>School grants and stipends which are used for food, clothing, and housing but not for books and tuition.
A federal income tax return is the preferred source for determining earnings. If a federal income tax return is not representative of current earnings, the county may also require pay stubs which include gross and net earnings.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 14; SL 2019, ch 216, § 34.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_8">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.8</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Household resources</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_8__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Equity value of the household's primary residence, excluding the homestead exemption provided for in subdivision 43-45-3</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_8__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Equity value of other real property;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_8__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Equity value of major recreational and other leisure equipment including watercraft, campers, recreational vehicles, all
-
terrain vehicles, and snowmobiles;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_8__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Equity value, in excess of five thousand dollars, of all motor vehicles;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_8__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Personal assets, including cash in excess of one
-
half month's income, stocks, securities, accounts and notes due the person or the person's household, cash values of life insurance policies, collectible judicial judgments in favor of the person or the person's household, and monetary gifts;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_8__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Equity value of business property, including real estate, equipment, and inventory; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_8__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Equity value of household goods and personal property beyond that which is reasonably essential for everyday living and self
-
support.
Equity value is determined by subtracting an asset's outstanding indebtedness from its fair market value.
The county shall subtract five thousand dollars from the total of the household's countable resources to determine the household's adjusted resources.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 15.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_9">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.9</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Determination of person's ability to pay--Factors</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_9__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Determine the household's contributions for taxes, social security, medicare, and payments to other standard retirement programs. A household's contribution for taxes is limited to the amount of taxes payable for the actual number of dependents in the household;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_9__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Determine the household's expenses, including actual rent paid or scheduled principal and interest payments for a personal residence plus property taxes and homeowner's insurance costs; all utilities; child care expenses related to work schedules; grocery expenses up to the maximum allowed under the Food Stamp Program's Thrifty Food Plan as specified in rules promulgated by the Department of Social Services pursuant to chapter
1-26
, plus household supplies and toiletries; basic auto expenses, gasoline, and upkeep; employee
-
paid health, life, and auto insurance payments; installment payments for medical bills; recurring expenses for medicine and medical care; court
-
ordered child support and alimony paid; automobile installment payments for one vehicle; clothing, reasonable in relation to the household's income; and installment payments, limited to necessary household items required by the household to maintain the needs of everyday living and reasonable in relation to the household's income;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_9__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Determine the amount of a household's discretionary income by subtracting the sum of the household's contributions and expenses from the household's income determined according to §
28-13-32.7
. Divide the amount of the household's discretionary income in half and multiply the resulting amount by forty
-
four dollars and ninety
-
six cents. The result added to the household's adjusted resources determined according to §
28-13-32.8
equals the household's ability to pay the debt and constitutes the household's share of the hospital bill. The amount of forty
-
four dollars and ninety
-
six cents represents the amount of medical or hospital expenses which can be amortized over sixty months at twelve percent annual interest per dollar of payment.
The amount of the county's obligation is determined by subtracting the amount of the household's ability to pay from the hospital charges computed according to §
28-13-29
. If the household defaults on the payment of its share of the hospital bill, a hospital may not pursue a collection action against the county for the defaulted payment.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 16; SL 1998, ch 165, § 2.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_10">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.10</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Indigency by design</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-32.10
.
Indigency by design.
If an individual is indigent by design, the individual is ineligible for medical assistance under the provisions of this chapter and there may be no other criteria used to determine eligibility.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 22.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_32_11">
            <akn:num>28-13-32.11</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Determination of household's ability to purchase health insurance</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_11__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Determine the household's income and resources according to §§
28-13-32.7
and
28-13-32.8
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_11__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Determine the household's contributions for taxes, social security, medicare, and payments to other standard retirement programs according to subdivision
28-13-32.9</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_11__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Except for the medical expenses for which the household is requesting assistance, determine the household's expenses according to subdivision
28-13-32.9</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_11__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Determine the amount of the household's discretionary income by subtracting the sum of the household's contributions and expenses from the household's income. Divide the amount of the household's discretionary income in half. The result added to the household's adjusted resources determined according to §
28-13-32.8
equals the household's discretionary income that was available to purchase health insurance;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_32_11__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Subtract the amount of the monthly health insurance premium that was available to the household if known or, if unknown, an estimate of the premium the household could be expected to incur. For purposes of this subdivision, the county shall establish such estimate either by obtaining premium estimates from two major medical insurance carriers doing business in the state or by using an estimate based on the rate data provided to the county by the Division of Insurance of the Department of Labor and Regulation. The policy used shall have a benefit design that equals or exceeds the benefit design of the basic benefit plan as developed by the Health Benefit Plan Committee pursuant to § 58-18B-32. If the result is a negative number, the health insurance was not affordable. If the result is a positive number, health insurance was affordable and the individual is considered to be indigent by design.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 134, § 2; SL 2004, ch 17, § 36; SL 2011, ch 1 (Ex. Ord.
11-1
), § 162, eff. Apr. 12, 2011.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_33">
            <akn:num>28-13-33</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>County liability for emergency and nonemergency hospitalization of indigent persons--Remedies for recovery of expense by county</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-33
.
County liability for emergency and nonemergency hospitalization of indigent persons--Remedies for recovery of expense by county.
Subject to the provisions of this chapter and except as expressly provided, if a hospital furnishes emergency hospital services to a medically indigent person, the county where the medically indigent person has established residency is liable to the hospital for the reimbursement of the hospitalization. In the case of nonemergency care, the county of residence is liable only to the extent that the board of county commissioners, in good faith, approves an application for assistance. If a county provides payment for nonemergency services, the services shall be approved by the county before the services are provided. To the extent that the county provides payment to a hospital, the county has the same remedies for the recovery of the expense as are provided by chapter
28-14
for the recovery of money expended for the relief and support of poor and indigent persons.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B03; SL 1976, ch 173, § 19; SL 1988, ch 226, § 2; SL 1997, ch 170, § 11.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_33_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-33.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Experimental procedures and treatment for medically indigent patient</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-33.1
.
Experimental procedures and treatment for medically indigent patient.
No county is liable for the payment of any experimental procedures or experimental modes of treatment provided on behalf of a medically indigent person.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 28.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_33_2">
            <akn:num>28-13-33.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Billing for care of medically indigent patients</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-33.2
.
Billing for care of medically indigent patients.
If submitting a bill to a county for medically necessary hospital services provided on behalf of a person who is medically indigent, the hospital must first demonstrate that it has exhausted all avenues of payment including accepting reasonable monthly payments from the person who does not have the ability to pay the hospital in one lump sum at the time of discharge.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 30.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_34">
            <akn:num>28-13-34</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-34</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-34.
Repealed by SL 1988, ch 226, § 7</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_34_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-34.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Notice to county where hospitalization is furnished to indigent person--Time for notice of emergency and nonemergency admissions--Contents of notice</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_34_1__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The name and last known address of the patient or the patient's guardian;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_34_1__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The name and address of the responsible party, if known;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_34_1__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The name of the attending physician;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_34_1__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The nature and degree of severity of the illness;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_34_1__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The anticipated diagnostic or therapeutic services required;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_34_1__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The location at which the services are to be provided;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_34_1__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The estimated reimbursement for the services; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_13_34_1__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>A statement that the hospital has asked the patient or the responsible party, if known, whether the patient has served in any branch of the military, is potentially eligible for Indian Health Service benefits, or is a member of a Native American tribe and a statement of the information received in response to the inquiry.
Source:
SL 1988, ch 226, § 1; SL 1989, ch 245; SL 1997, ch 170, § 17.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_34_2">
            <akn:num>28-13-34.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Release of information</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-34.2
.
Release of information.
If submitting a notice under the provisions of §
28-13-34.1
, the hospital shall make every reasonable effort to secure from the patient, and to include with the notice, a release of information form which has been signed by the patient or the patient's authorized representative. The form shall authorize persons, agencies, or institutions to release, to the county, the patient's social security number, the social security number of other household members, medical information concerning the patient, and financial information concerning the patient or members of the patient's household.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 26.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_35">
            <akn:num>28-13-35</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Substitute arrangements for hospitalized indigent patient--County not liable to hospital after failure to cooperate</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-35
.
Substitute arrangements for hospitalized indigent patient--County not liable to hospital after failure to cooperate.
In any case of hospitalization of a medically indigent person, the county, through any elected officer or through an employee, may arrange for adequate and suitable care of the person elsewhere. If the county notifies the hospital in writing of its arrangement for the removal of the medically indigent person and the hospital unreasonably fails or refuses to cooperate in effecting the change, the county is not liable for any hospitalization subsequent to the hospital's failure or refusal to cooperate.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 4; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B04; SL 1997, ch 170, § 18.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_36">
            <akn:num>28-13-36</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Contractual arrangements between county and hospital not impaired</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-36
.
Contractual arrangements between county and hospital not impaired.
Nothing in this chapter precludes a hospital and a county from entering into a reasonable and suitable arrangement, contract, or agreement for hospitalization of medically indigent persons at other rates than provided under this chapter, or abrogates or impairs any rights or remedies of either the county or the hospital under any such arrangement, contract, or agreement.
Source:
SL 1953, ch 131, § 5; SDC Supp 1960, § 27.12B05; SL 1997, ch 170, § 19.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_37">
            <akn:num>28-13-37</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>County duty to relieve nonresidents in distress</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-37
.
County duty to relieve nonresidents in distress.
It shall be the duty of the county commissioners, on complaint made to them that any person not an inhabitant of their county is lying sick therein or in distress, without friends or money, so that he is likely to suffer, to examine into the case of such person and grant such temporary relief as the nature of the case may require.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0105.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_37_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-37.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Medical review by county or Department of Social Services</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-37.1
.
Medical review by county or Department of Social Services.
A county may review the need for emergency room treatment, an admission, a transfer, a continued stay, or inpatient surgical services. At its option, a county may request the Department of Social Services to provide the needed reviews on the county's behalf. In either case, the review shall be conducted by or under the supervision of a physician licensed under chapter
36-4
, and shall be consistent with generally accepted medical practice guidelines.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 170, § 27.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_38">
            <akn:num>28-13-38</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Temporary relief to nonresident--Reimbursement by home county</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-38
.
Temporary relief to nonresident--Reimbursement by home county.
Whenever any person entitled to temporary relief as a poor person shall be in any county in which he has not established residency, the commissioners thereof may, if the same is deemed advisable, grant such relief by providing the same relief as is customary in cases where persons have established residency in the state and county. The county furnishing relief shall be entitled to reimbursements from the county in which said poor person has established residency.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0104; SL 1941, ch 211, § 4; SL 1976, ch 173, § 20.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_38_1">
            <akn:num>28-13-38.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>When hospitals outside state are eligible for reimbursement by county</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-38.1
.
When hospitals outside state are eligible for reimbursement by county.
Hospitals located outside South Dakota are eligible for reimbursement from the county where the medically indigent person has established residency only if the hospital provides services which are not available in South Dakota or the hospital is approved by the county of residence of the medically indigent person as providing a reasonable or cost
-
effective service.
Source:
SL 1988, ch 225, § 2; SL 1997, ch 170, § 20.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_39">
            <akn:num>28-13-39</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-39</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-39.
Repealed by SL 1976, ch 173, § 35</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_40">
            <akn:num>28-13-40</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Appeal to circuit court from county commissioners--Direction for assistance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-40
.
Appeal to circuit court from county commissioners--Direction for assistance.
If any person shall suppose that he is entitled to the benefit of the laws for the relief of the poor, and the commissioners of the county in which he applies for assistance shall refuse to give such person the benefit thereof, upon application of such person a judge of the circuit court having jurisdiction over such county may, if he shall think proper, direct such commissioners to provide assistance pursuant to this chapter to such person.
Source:
SDC 1939, § 50.0208; SL 1976, ch 173, § 21.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_41">
            <akn:num>28-13-41</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-13-41</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-41.
Repealed by SL 2013, ch 127, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_42">
            <akn:num>28-13-42</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Names of recipients not released for publication</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-42
.
Names of recipients not released for publication.
The county auditor or any other county official shall not release the name of any poor relief recipient for official publication.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 79, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_43">
            <akn:num>28-13-43</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Assignment or transfer of property to qualify for assistance as misdemeanor</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-43
.
Assignment or transfer of property to qualify for assistance as misdemeanor.
At any time before or after making an application for poor relief, an applicant may not assign or transfer any property for the purpose of becoming eligible for assistance under this chapter. Violation of this section is a Class 1 misdemeanor.
Source:
SL 1980, ch 202, § 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_13_44">
            <akn:num>28-13-44</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Bankruptcy not admissible in making determination of indigency</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-13-44
.
Bankruptcy not admissible in making determination of indigency.
The fact that an individual has filed a petition in bankruptcy or has received a discharge in bankruptcy under Title 11 of the United States Code is not admissible evidence in a proceeding under this chapter and may not be considered in making a determination of indigency.
Source:
SL 1995, ch 166; SL 1997, ch 170, § 21.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_5">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-5</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Medical Assistance for the Aged</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_5_1">
            <akn:num>28-5-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-5-1 to 28-5-23</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-5-1 to 28-5-23.
Repealed by SL 1968, ch 208</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_5_24">
            <akn:num>28-5-24</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Supplemental services to complement provisions of Title XVIII of the 1965 amendments to the federal Social Security Act, as amended</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-5-24
.
Supplemental services to complement provisions of Title XVIII of the 1965 amendments to the federal Social Security Act, as amended.
The Department of Social Services may provide medical services and medical or remedial care to or on behalf of any medically indigent person of this state who has attained the age of sixty
-
five years, in such manner as to complement the provisions of Title XVIII of the 1965 amendments to the federal Social Security Act, as amended to January 1, 2004, to the end that the medical needs of any such person may be adequately met.
Source:
SL 1966, ch 190, § 1; SL 2004, ch 167, § 48.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_5_25">
            <akn:num>28-5-25</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-5-25</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-5-25.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 199, § 30</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_5_26">
            <akn:num>28-5-26</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-5-26</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-5-26.
Repealed by SL 2004, ch 167, § 49</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_5A">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-5A</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Supplemental Security Income</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_5A_1">
            <akn:num>28-5A-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Agreements to administer supplemental security income programs--Rules for payments to qualified residents</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-5A-1
.
Agreements to administer supplemental security income programs--Rules for payments to qualified residents.
In addition to the other powers granted to the Department of Social Services under chapter
28-1
, the department may cooperate with or enter into agreements with agencies of the federal government to the extent necessary or appropriate to implement the provisions of Public Law 92-603, Social Security Amendments of 1972, as amended to January 1, 2004, including the power to agree to administer all or part of the supplemental security income program of the federal government, to provide, under such rules as may be promulgated by the department, for supplementary payments to qualified residents of South Dakota who are receiving or would be eligible to receive supplemental security income under Title XVI of the Social Security Amendments of 1972, as amended to January 1, 2004, or any other agreement which would be of benefit to the citizens of this state.
Source:
SL 1973, ch 176, § 1; SL 2004, ch 167, § 50.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_5A_2">
            <akn:num>28-5A-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Reimbursement of administrative costs--Federal funds for benefit payments</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-5A-2
.
Reimbursement of administrative costs--Federal funds for benefit payments.
The Department of Social Services shall be reimbursed in full under any agreement for its costs of administration of any federal program and when necessary shall be provided with federal funds sufficient to meet benefit payment obligations for recipients under the terms of any agreement entered into pursuant to this chapter.
Source:
SL 1973, ch 176, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_6">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-6</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Medical Services to the Indigent</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_1">
            <akn:num>28-6-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Provision of medical services and remedial care authorized--Rules</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_1__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The amount, scope, and duration of medical and remedial services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_1__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The basis for and extent of provider payments on behalf of an eligible person;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_1__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The establishment and collection of copayments, premiums, fees, or charges for sharing the cost of risk protection or services provided to persons. All such collections shall be remitted to the general fund;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_1__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Methods of administration found necessary for the operation of the medical assistance program;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_1__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Safeguards against the disclosure or improper use of information, required by statutory law to be held confidential, concerning applicants for or recipients of medical assistance; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_1__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Such other requirements as may be necessary to obtain federal financial participation in the medical assistance program.
Source:
SL 1966, ch 191, § 1; SL 1981, ch 199, § 31; SL 1982, ch 203, § 1; SL 1987, ch 29, § 10; SL 2000, ch 132, § 10; SL 2004, ch 167, § 51; SL 2019, ch 127, § 9.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_1_1">
            <akn:num>28-6-1.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Establishment of fee schedules--Posting of fees, changes--Applicability of chapter 1-26</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-1.1
.
Establishment of fee schedules--Posting of fees, changes--Applicability of chapter
1-26
.
The Department of Social Services may establish or amend fee schedules used to pay for items and services covered by the medical assistance program under the provisions of this chapter without following the procedures set forth in §§
1-26-4
to
1-26-6
, inclusive. The department shall post the fee schedules on the department's website and shall notify website users of pending changes by posting a notice of the pending changes on the website at least forty
-
eight hours before the changes are made. Fee schedules posted on the department's website must be in accordance with the department's administrative rules promulgated under the provisions of chapter
1-26
which establish the reimbursement provisions for medical services.
Source:
SL 2003, ch 156, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_1_2">
            <akn:num>28-6-1.2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Reimbursement schedule for certain services--Medicaid program</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-1.2
.
Reimbursement schedule for certain services--Medicaid program.
The Department of Social Services shall establish, maintain, and publish a reimbursement schedule for chiropractic, dental, and optometric services delivered under the Medicaid program. The schedule shall provide a reimbursement amount for each service.
The department shall determine reimbursement amounts, for each service, based on a percentage of current normal and customary fees in this state.
The department may seek the assistance of third parties to determine current normal and customary fees.
The department shall promulgate rules, pursuant to chapter
1-26
, to establish and annually adjust the reimbursement schedule.
Source:
SL 2022, ch 87, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_2">
            <akn:num>28-6-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-2</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-2.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 199, § 33</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_3">
            <akn:num>28-6-3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-3</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-3.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 166, § 21</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_3_1">
            <akn:num>28-6-3.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Disposal of assets at less than fair market value--Effect on eligibility</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_3_1__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The period of ineligibility when real or personal assets are given away or sold at less than fair market value;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_3_1__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Exemptions; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_3_1__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Such other standards and requirements as may be necessary for federal financial participation.
Source:
SL 1981, ch 213, § 1; SL 1984, ch 200; SL 1989, ch 242, § 1; SL 1994, ch 228; SL 2007, ch 171, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_4">
            <akn:num>28-6-4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-4</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-4.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 199, § 34</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_4_1">
            <akn:num>28-6-4.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-4</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-4.1 to 28-6-4.4.
Repealed by SL 1971, ch 169, § 1</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_4_5">
            <akn:num>28-6-4.5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Public funds not to be used for abortion except to save life of mother</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-4.5
.
Public funds not to be used for abortion except to save life of mother.
No funds of the State of South Dakota or any agency, county, municipality, or any other political subdivision thereof and no federal funds passing through the state treasury or any agency of the State of South Dakota, county, municipality, or any other political subdivision thereof, shall be authorized or paid to or on behalf of any person or entity for or in connection with any abortion that is not necessary for the preservation of the life of the person upon whom the abortion is performed.
Source:
SL 1978, ch 207.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_4_6">
            <akn:num>28-6-4.6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-4</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-4.6.
Repealed by SL 2018, ch 160, § 3.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_5">
            <akn:num>28-6-5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Opportunity provided to apply for assistance--Assistance furnished promptly</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-5
.
Opportunity provided to apply for assistance--Assistance furnished promptly.
Any person may apply for medical assistance, and assistance shall be furnished with reasonable promptness to those who are eligible.
Source:
SL 1966, ch 191, § 4 (1); SL 1981, ch 199, § 32.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_5_1">
            <akn:num>28-6-5.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-5</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-5.1.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 199, § 35</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_6">
            <akn:num>28-6-6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Fair hearing on denial or delay in assistance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-6
.
Fair hearing on denial or delay in assistance.
The department shall promulgate rules pursuant to chapter
1-26
requiring an opportunity for fair hearing before the Department of Social Services by any individual whose claim for assistance is denied or not acted upon with reasonable promptness.
Source:
SL 1966, ch 191, § 4(2); SL 2004, ch 167, § 52.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_7">
            <akn:num>28-6-7</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-7</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-7.
Repealed by SL 1994, ch 229, § 1</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_7_1">
            <akn:num>28-6-7.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Acceptance of assistance as assignment and subrogation of support rights and insurance proceeds--Liability of insurer or attorney</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-7.1
.
Acceptance of assistance as assignment and subrogation of support rights and insurance proceeds--Liability of insurer or attorney.
An application for or acceptance of medical assistance paid from the Department of Social Services shall operate as an assignment and subrogation by operation of law of any rights to medical support, insurance proceeds, or both, that the applicant or recipient may have for the applicant's or recipient's person, spouse, or child. This assignment and subrogation includes all claims or actions for damages, either general or special. An application for or acceptance of medical assistance from the Department of Social Services shall be deemed by an applicant or recipient and any insurance provider, including self
-
insurance, as a release of information authorizing the release of insurance coverage information to the Department of Social Services regardless of the policyholder. Any rights or amounts so assigned or subrogated shall be applied against the cost of medical care paid under this chapter, less all reasonable expenses, including attorney's fees incurred by the applicant or recipient to collect such support or proceeds. Any insurance provider or attorney in fact who, after notice, fails to recognize or accept an assignment or subrogation established by operation of law by this section is liable to the Department of Social Services for the full amount of medical assistance paid to or on behalf of the applicant or recipient by the department for the accident, injury, or illness for which collection is claimed or made.
Source:
SL 1977, ch 220; SL 1991, ch 223; SL 1993, ch 208; SL 2004, ch 167, § 53.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_8">
            <akn:num>28-6-8</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-8 to 28-6-10</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-8 to 28-6-10.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 199, §§ 36 to 38</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_11">
            <akn:num>28-6-11</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-11</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-11.
Omitted</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_12">
            <akn:num>28-6-12</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-12 to 28-6-15</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-12 to 28-6-15.
Repealed by SL 1985, ch 223, §§ 1 to 4</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_16">
            <akn:num>28-6-16</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Definition of terms</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Community spouse," the spouse of an institutionalized spouse;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Deeming" or "deemed," the determination by the department that nonexempt resources or income of a spouse is available to an institutionalized spouse;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Department," the Department of Social Services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Exempt income," any income which may not be considered in determining eligibility for medical assistance pursuant to §
28-6-1
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Exempt resources," any resources which may not be considered in determining eligibility for medical assistance pursuant to §
28-6-1
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Income," any earned or unearned income under rules adopted pursuant to §
28-6-1
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Institutionalized spouse," an individual who is applying for or receiving long
-
term care and is married to a spouse who is not in long
-
term care;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Long
-
term care," skilled nursing care and related services for residents who require medical or nursing care; rehabilitation services for the rehabilitation of injured, disabled or sick persons; or on a regular basis, health
-
related care and services to individuals who because of their mental or physical condition require care and services above the level of room and board which can be made available to them only through institutional facilities, and is not primarily for the care and treatment of mental disease;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_9">
              <akn:num>(9)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Nonexempt income," any income which may be considered in determining eligibility for medical assistance pursuant to §
28-6-1
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_10">
              <akn:num>(10)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Nonexempt resources," any resources which may be considered in determining eligibility for medical assistance pursuant to §
28-6-1
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_11">
              <akn:num>(11)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Resources," any cash or other liquid assets or any real or personal property under rules adopted pursuant to §
28-6-1
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_16__subsec_12">
              <akn:num>(12)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Spousal share," the amount of nonexempt income or resources unavailable to an institutionalized spouse, for the purposes of determining eligibility for long
-
term care, under §§
28-6-16
to
28-6-22
, inclusive.
Source:
SL 1989, ch 243, § 1; SL 1990, ch 208, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_17">
            <akn:num>28-6-17</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Income and resources of spouses in long-term care--Division--Notice--Hearing</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-17
.
Income and resources of spouses in long
-
term care--Division--Notice--Hearing.
The department shall determine the aggregate nonexempt resources and income of the community spouse and the institutionalized spouse at the beginning of a continuous period of institutionalization of the institutionalized spouse regardless of whether an application for long
-
term medical assistance is made at the time. After the aggregate nonexempt resources and income have been determined, the department shall determine a spousal share. The department shall notify the institutionalized spouse and the community spouse of the division of income and resources for the purpose of deeming in long
-
term care. If either the institutionalized spouse or the community spouse is dissatisfied with the division of income or resources, that spouse is entitled to a fair hearing pursuant to §
28-6-6
if there is an application for long
-
term care medical assistance. If an application for long
-
term care medical assistance is not made the department may charge a reasonable fee for its assessment.
Source:
SL 1989, ch 243, § 3.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_18">
            <akn:num>28-6-18</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Promulgation of rules regarding income and resources in long-term care</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_18__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The determination of exempt and nonexempt income in long-term care;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_18__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The treatment of income in long-term care;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_18__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The deeming of income in long-term care;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_18__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The determination of the spousal minimum monthly allowance in long-term care;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_18__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The determination of the spousal share of resources; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_18__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Such other standards and requirements as may be necessary for federal financial participation.
Source:
SL 1989, ch 243, § 2; SL 2004, ch 167, § 54; SL 2019, ch 127, § 10.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_19">
            <akn:num>28-6-19</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6-19</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-19.
Repealed by SL 2004, ch 167, § 55</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_20">
            <akn:num>28-6-20</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Effect of 28-6-16 to 28-6-22, inclusive, on other statutes</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-20
.
Effect of
28-6-16
to
28-6-22
, inclusive, on other statutes.
The provisions of §§
28-6-16
to
28-6-22
, inclusive, do not affect any state statute concerning the duty to support a spouse.
Sections
28-6-16
to
28-6-22
, inclusive, do not affect any state statute concerning the transfer of assets for the purpose of establishing eligibility for the medical assistance program.
Source:
SL 1989, ch 243, §§ 5, 6.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_22">
            <akn:num>28-6-22</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Application of 28-6-16 to 28-6-22, inclusive</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-22
.
Application of
28-6-16
to
28-6-22
, inclusive.
The deeming of income under §§
28-6-16
to
28-6-22
, inclusive, applies to individuals institutionalized on or after September 30, 1989.
Source:
SL 1989, ch 243, § 8.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_21">
            <akn:num>28-6-21</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Application of 28-6-17</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-21
.
Application of
28-6-17
.
The determination of the spousal share of resources under §
28-6-17
applies only to institutionalized individuals who begin continuous periods of institutionalization on or after September 30, 1989.
Source:
SL 1989, ch 243, § 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_23">
            <akn:num>28-6-23</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Medical assistance as debt to department--Recovery of debt</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-23
.
Medical assistance as debt to department--Recovery of debt.
Any payment of medical assistance by or through the Department of Social Services to an individual who is an inpatient in a nursing facility, an intermediate care facility for individuals with developmental disabilities, or other medical institution, is a debt due to the department. Any payment on behalf of any person fifty-five years of age or older for nursing facility services, home and community based services, intermediate care facility services for individuals with intellectual disabilities, hospital and prescription drug services, is a debt due the department. The Department of Social Services shall establish a system of recovery of medical assistance correctly paid by or through the department. The Department of Social Services may file a claim against the estate of the surviving spouse of a medical assistance recipient to satisfy the debt established under this section. The secretary of social services shall adopt rules, pursuant to chapter
1-26
, to define the scope of recoveries, establish hardship limitations on recoveries, establish limits on recoveries, and provide rules required to obtain federal financial participation in the medical assistance program.
For the purposes of this section, a surviving spouse is a person who was married to the deceased medical assistance recipient when the recipient became eligible for medical assistance, who has not divorced the medical assistance recipient, and who has not remarried after the recipient's death.
Source:
SL 1994, ch 229, § 7; SL 1997, ch 168, § 1; SL 2013, ch 125, § 12.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_23_1">
            <akn:num>28-6-23.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Limiting financial responsibility of estate of surviving spouse</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-23.1
.
Limiting financial responsibility of estate of surviving spouse.
A surviving spouse may petition the Department of Social Services for purposes of limiting the financial responsibility of the estate of the surviving spouse. The financial responsibility of the estate of the surviving spouse may not exceed the value of the estate of the surviving spouse as of the date of death of the medical assistance recipient. For purposes of the determination of the financial responsibility, it shall be assumed that the surviving spouse died simultaneously with the medical assistance recipient. The petition for financial responsibility shall be filed with the Department of Social Services within six months of the date of death of the medical assistance recipient.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 168, § 2.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_24">
            <akn:num>28-6-24</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Medical assistance lien against real property</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-24
.
Medical assistance lien against real property.
Any payment of medical assistance by or through the Department of Social Services to an individual who is an inpatient in a nursing facility, an intermediate care facility for individuals with intellectual disabilities, or other medical institution is a debt and creates a medical assistance lien against any real property in which the individual has any ownership interest. The secretary of social services shall adopt reasonable and necessary rules, pursuant to chapter
1-26
, to define such individuals, establish the amount of the lien, establish limitations on the lien as required by federal law or regulations, and provide any other rules as may be required to obtain federal financial participation in the medical assistance program. The lien so created shall be perfected against real estate as provided in §
28-6-25
.
Source:
SL 1994, ch 229, § 2; SL 2013, ch 125, § 13.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_25">
            <akn:num>28-6-25</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Filing medical assistance real estate lien</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_25__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The name and last known address of all owners of the real property;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_25__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The legal description of the real estate to which the lien is to attach;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_25__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The circumstances out of which the lien is claimed to have arisen and the circumstances, if any, under which future accumulations may arise;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_25__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The amount claimed as a lien and the probable amounts by which it may increase, if known.
The register of deeds shall, without charge to the department, record the medical assistance real estate lien in the real estate records, at which time the lien will attach to the real property interest of the recipient described in subdivision</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_25__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>of this section. The lien shall remain in effect for a period of twenty years from the time of recording in the county where the land is located as provided in this section, unless released or foreclosed as provided by law.
If the individual is discharged or released from a nursing facility, intermediate care facility for individuals with intellectual disabilities, or other medical institution, other than by death or transfer to another or similar institution, the Department of Social Services shall immediately, upon notice of the discharge or release, file with the register of deeds a satisfaction of the lien which shall be recorded by the register of deeds in the real estate records without charge.
Source:
SL 1994, ch 229, § 3; SL 2013, ch 125, § 14.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_26">
            <akn:num>28-6-26</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Exemption to medical assistance lien</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-26
.
Exemption to medical assistance lien.
Real estate deemed available to a community spouse pursuant to §§
28-6-17
to
28-6-22
, inclusive, is not subject to the medical assistance lien.
Source:
SL 1994, ch 229, § 4.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_27">
            <akn:num>28-6-27</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Priority of medical assistance lien</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-27
.
Priority of medical assistance lien.
The priority of the medical assistance real estate lien shall be established as of the time of recording by the register of deeds.
Source:
SL 1994, ch 229, § 5.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_28">
            <akn:num>28-6-28</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Definition of terms</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Department," the Department of Social Services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Fiscal period," up to a twelve
-
month period determined by the department;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Funding pool," pool of funds established in accordance with §
28-6-29
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Health care trust fund," the fund established as provided in S.D. Const., Art. XII, § 5 to hold the federal portion of the monetary difference between the medicaid payment and the medicare upper limits maximum allowable reimbursement, less transaction fees paid to publicly owned and operated nursing facilities;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Medical assistance," the medicaid program authorized by Title XIX of the Social Security Act, 42 U.S.C. 1396d, as amended through January 1, 2004, which provides medical assistance to eligible individuals and is operated under §
28-6-1
;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Medicare," the Health Insurance for the Aged Act, Title XVIII of the Social Security Amendments of 1965 and as amended through January 1, 2004;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Nursing facility," any facility participating in medicaid that is licensed, maintained, and operated for the express or implied purpose of providing care to one or more persons, whether for consideration or not, who are not acutely ill but require nursing care and related medical services of such complexity as to require professional nursing care under the direction of a physician twenty
-
four hours a day;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Political subdivision," any municipality or county;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_28__subsec_9">
              <akn:num>(9)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Publicly owned and operated nursing facility," a nursing facility that is owned and operated by a political subdivision of the state and is participating in medicaid.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 132, § 1; SL 2001, ch 152, § 2; SL 2004, ch 167, § 56.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_29">
            <akn:num>28-6-29</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Funding pool established</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-29
.
Funding pool established.
The department shall establish a funding pool consisting of an amount annually calculated by multiplying the total of all medical assistance resident days of all publicly owned and operated nursing facilities during the fiscal period during which a resident was eligible for and received benefits under chapter
28-6
times an amount that does not exceed the amount that can reasonably be estimated to be paid under payment principles established under medicare, reduced by the medical assistance payment rates set for each such resident, for each such day, during the fiscal period.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 132, § 2; SL 2003, ch 155, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_30">
            <akn:num>28-6-30</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Payments from funding pool to publicly owned and operated nursing facilities</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_30__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Dividing that facility's total medical assistance resident days for the fiscal period by the total medical assistance resident days of all publicly owned and operated nursing facilities participating under the provisions of §§
28-6-28
to
28-6-36
, inclusive, for the fiscal period; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_30__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Multiplying a decimal fraction determined under subdivision</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_31">
            <akn:num>28-6-31</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Payments to be remitted to department for credit to health care trust fund</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_31__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The health care trust fund as provided in S.D. Const., Art. XII, § 5 in an amount equal to the applicable federal medical assistance percentage times the total remittance to the department, less the transaction fee; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_31__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The department's other funds for all remaining amounts.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 132, § 4; SL 2001, ch 152, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_32">
            <akn:num>28-6-32</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Publicly owned and operated nursing facility may receive and shall remit payments under §§ 28-6-30 and 28-6-31--Exception</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-32
.
Publicly owned and operated nursing facility may receive and shall remit payments under §§
28-6-30
and
28-6-31
--Exception.
Notwithstanding any other provision of law governing the operation of a publicly owned and operated nursing facility, a publicly owned and operated nursing facility participating under the provisions of §§
28-6-28
to
28-6-36
, inclusive, may receive and immediately upon receipt shall remit payments provided under §§
28-6-30
and
28-6-31
. No payment is required under this section for any period in which the use of funds for the purposes of §§
28-6-28
to
28-6-36
, inclusive, are prohibited due to action by the secretary of the United States Department of Health and Human Services.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 132, § 5.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_33">
            <akn:num>28-6-33</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Code provisions governing investment in health care trust fund</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-33
.
Code provisions governing investment in health care trust fund.
The investment of moneys in the health care trust fund as provided in S.D. Const. Art., XII, § 5 is not restricted by the provisions of §
4-5-26
, but is governed by the provisions of §
4-5-27
.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 132, § 6; SL 2001, ch 152, § 4.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_34">
            <akn:num>28-6-34</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Funds appropriated under § 28-6-1 may be used for payments under § 28-6-30</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-34
.
Funds appropriated under §
28-6-1
may be used for payments under §
28-6-30
.
Funds appropriated to the department for purposes authorized under §
28-6-1
may be used for the purposes of making payments pursuant to §
28-6-30
each fiscal year.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 132, § 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_35">
            <akn:num>28-6-35</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Promulgation of rules regarding health care trust fund and funding pool</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-35
.
Promulgation of rules regarding health care trust fund and funding pool.
The department may promulgate rules pursuant to chapter
1-26
for the administration of §§
28-6-28
to
28-6-36
, inclusive. The rules may include criteria for establishing, funding, and administering the pool, criteria for participation in the intergovernmental transfer, penalties for failing to immediately remit the funds to the department, criteria for the transfer of funds, the establishment of transaction fees, and other policies to facilitate the administration of the health care trust fund or the funding pool.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 132, § 8; SL 2001, ch 152, § 3.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_36">
            <akn:num>28-6-36</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>No entitlement to funds</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-36
.
No entitlement to funds.
Sections
28-6-28
to
28-6-36
, inclusive, do not create an entitlement to any funds. The department may disburse funds to the extent funds are available and, within its discretion, to the extent such appropriations are approved.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 132, § 9.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_37">
            <akn:num>28-6-37</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Eligibility for nursing and rehabilitative services--Countable assets reduced by long-term care partnership program policy benefits</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6-37
.
Eligibility for nursing and rehabilitative services--Countable assets reduced by long-term care partnership program policy benefits.
When determining eligibility for nursing and rehabilitative services, if the individual is a beneficiary of an approved long-term care partnership program policy, the total countable assets of the individual shall be reduced by one dollar for each one dollar of benefits paid out under the individual's approved long-term care partnership program policy. The Department of Social Services is authorized to seek any federal waivers to implement this policy.
Source:
SL 2006, ch 149, § 1; SL 2008, ch 142, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6_38">
            <akn:num>28-6-38</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>South Dakota long-term care partnership program established</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_38__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Incentives for an individual to obtain insurance to cover the costs of long-term care;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_38__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Standards for long-term care insurance policies for designation as approved long-term care partnership program policies. The Division of Insurance shall assist in ensuring that these standards are appropriate. Any insurer offering any long-term care partnership program policy shall file the policy and any advertisements with the Division of Insurance in accordance with the applicable requirements of Title 58 and subject to the standards set by the Department of Social Services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_38__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>A mechanism to qualify for coverage of the costs of long-term care needs under medicaid without first being required to substantially exhaust his or her resources, including a reduction of the individual's asset valuation by one dollar for each one dollar of benefits paid out under the individual's approved long-term care partnership program policy as a determination of medicaid eligibility;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_38__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Inflation protection as provided by federal law;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_38__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Asset protection up to the maximum as provided by federal law;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_38__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Distribution of information regarding long-term care partnership plan policies to individuals through insurance companies offering approved partnership policies. The department shall approve the information before its distribution; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6_38__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Encouraging the pursuit of private initiatives to alleviate the financial burden on the state's medical assistance program. (Pursuant to SL 2006, ch 149, § 4, this section becomes effective upon passage of an amendment to section 1917 (b)</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_6A">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-6A</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Assistance in Treatment of Kidney Disease</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_1">
            <akn:num>28-6A-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6A-1</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-1.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 214, § 5</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_2">
            <akn:num>28-6A-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Dialysis and transplant program to be established--Assistance rendered</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-2
.
Dialysis and transplant program to be established--Assistance rendered.
The Department of Social Services shall establish a program for the care and treatment of persons suffering from chronic renal failure requiring dialysis or a transplant. The department shall assist persons who require lifesaving care and treatment for renal failure, but have insufficient income and resources to pay for these services.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 219, § 2; SL 1981, ch 214, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_3">
            <akn:num>28-6A-3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6A-3</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-3.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 214, § 6</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_4">
            <akn:num>28-6A-4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-4
.
Repealed.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 219, § 4 (4); SL 2023, ch 94, § 15.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_5">
            <akn:num>28-6A-5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-5
.
Repealed.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 219, § 4 (5); SL 2023, ch 94, § 16.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_6">
            <akn:num>28-6A-6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6A-6</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-6.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 214, § 7</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_7">
            <akn:num>28-6A-7</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6A-7</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-7.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 199, § 39; SL 1981, ch 214, § 8</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_8">
            <akn:num>28-6A-8</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Financial assistance to chronic renal failure patients--Services and supplies--Limitations</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-8
.
Financial assistance to chronic renal failure patients--Services and supplies--Limitations.
The secretary of social services shall extend financial assistance to persons suffering from chronic renal failure requiring dialysis or a transplant to help them obtain the medical, nursing, pharmaceutical, and technical services and supplies necessary for dialysis or transplants, including the renting or purchase of home dialysis equipment. Assistance may not exceed five thousand dollars annually for each eligible patient. Assistance for chronic renal failure may not exceed the amount that would be allowed for similar care and treatment under the medical assistance program authorized by chapter
28-6
. A patient is not eligible for assistance under this chapter until the patient has exhausted all other sources of assistance, including veteran's administration benefits, medical or hospital insurance, third
-
party liability, assistance under Titles XVIII or XIX of the Social Security Act, or other public or private benefits or assistance. Eligibility for assistance under chapter
28-13
is not considered as a source of assistance for purposes of this section.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 219, § 4 (3); SL 1981, ch 214, § 2; SL 1995, ch 165.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_9">
            <akn:num>28-6A-9</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-6A-9</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-9.
Repealed by SL 1981, ch 214, § 9</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_10">
            <akn:num>28-6A-10</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Contracts authorized for assistance from other agencies</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-10
.
Contracts authorized for assistance from other agencies.
The secretary of the Department of Social Services may contract with any appropriate agency for assistance in carrying out the purposes of this chapter.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 219, § 5; SL 2004, ch 167, § 57.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_11">
            <akn:num>28-6A-11</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-11
.
Repealed.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 219, § 9; SL 2023, ch 94, § 17.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_12">
            <akn:num>28-6A-12</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Rules for administration and enforcement</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-12
.
Rules for administration and enforcement.
The secretary of social services may promulgate rules pursuant to chapter
1-26
to properly administer and enforce the provisions of this chapter. The rules may include eligibility for assistance, income and resource limitations, methods of administration and record keeping, and the scope and limitation of services to be provided.
Source:
SL 1976, ch 219, § 6; SL 1981, ch 199, § 40; SL 1981, ch 214, § 3; SL 2004, ch 167, § 58.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6A_13">
            <akn:num>28-6A-13</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Schedule for copayment of service fees--Payments by applicant and department</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6A-13
.
Schedule for copayment of service fees--Payments by applicant and department.
The secretary of social services shall adopt by rule a copayment schedule for services under this chapter. The schedule shall consider the income and resources of the applicant or recipient. The applicant or recipient shall pay the copayment directly to the service provider. The Department of Social Services shall pay to the service provider the remainder of the amount of benefits to which the applicant or recipient is entitled under this chapter.
Source:
SL 1981, ch 214, § 4; SL 1982, ch 206.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_6B">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-6B</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Medical Care for Unborn Children</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6B_1">
            <akn:num>28-6B-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Prenatal care program created</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6B-1
.
Prenatal care program created.
There is hereby created the prenatal care program, a separate health assistance program, solely to provide for the medical care of unborn children whose mothers are ineligible for coverage under Title XIX of the federal Social Security Act based on their citizenship status.
Source:
SL 2016, ch 148, § 1; SL 2019, ch 127, § 11.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6B_2">
            <akn:num>28-6B-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6B-2
.
Repealed.
Source:
SL 2016, ch 148, § 2; SL 2023, ch 94, § 18.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6B_3">
            <akn:num>28-6B-3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Administration by department</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6B-3
.
Administration by department.
The department shall implement the prenatal care program and shall receive and distribute the state and federal funds appropriated or provided for benefits pursuant to this chapter.
Source:
SL 2016, ch 148, § 3.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6B_4">
            <akn:num>28-6B-4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Promulgation of rules</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6B_4__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The amount, scope, and duration of prenatal medical services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6B_4__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The basis for and extent of provider payments on behalf of an eligible person;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6B_4__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The establishment and collection of copayments, premiums, fees, or charges for sharing the cost of risk protection or services to persons. All collections shall be remitted to the general fund;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6B_4__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Methods of administration found necessary for the operation of the prenatal care program;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6B_4__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Safeguards against the disclosure or improper use of information, required by statutory law to be held confidential, concerning applicants for or recipients of medical assistance; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_6B_4__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Any other requirements as may be necessary to obtain federal financial participation in the medical assistance program.
Source:
SL 2016, ch 148, § 4; SL 2019, ch 127, § 12.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6B_5">
            <akn:num>28-6B-5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Eligibility for program</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6B-5
.
Eligibility for program.
The department shall determine eligibility for this program using the same income limits and methodology used to determine eligibility for the pregnancy program under Title XIX.
Source:
SL 2016, ch 148, § 5.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6B_6">
            <akn:num>28-6B-6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Scope of services</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6B-6
.
Scope of services.
The department shall determine the scope of services eligible to provide health coverage for the unborn child for this program in accordance with the federal regulations.
Source:
SL 2016, ch 148, § 6.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6B_7">
            <akn:num>28-6B-7</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Medical issue unrelated to pregnancy not included</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6B-7
.
Medical issue unrelated to pregnancy not included.
No medical services for a medical issue unrelated to the pregnancy or separate to the mother is covered under this chapter.
Source:
SL 2016, ch 148, § 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_6B_8">
            <akn:num>28-6B-8</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Abortion not included--Exception</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-6B-8
.
Abortion not included--Exception.
For purposes of this chapter, the term, prenatal medical services, does not include an abortion unless the abortion is necessitated by a medical emergency as defined in subdivision 34-23A-1(5).
Source:
SL 2016, ch 148, § 8.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_7A">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-7A</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Temporary Assistance for Needy Families</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_1">
            <akn:num>28-7A-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>No entitlement to assistance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-1
.
No entitlement to assistance.
The implementation of assistance under this chapter does not establish a personal or family entitlement to assistance.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_2">
            <akn:num>28-7A-2</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Definition of terms</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_2__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Assistance," includes money, services, goods, or other types of temporary assistance made with respect to any child or with respect to the parents of any child for whom federal funds are available to the state under this chapter;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_2__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Department," the Department of Social Services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_2__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Title IV," including its derivatives, refers to Title IV of the federal Social Security Act.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 2.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_3">
            <akn:num>28-7A-3</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Promulgation of rules</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Assistance eligibility qualifications except as otherwise provided in §
28-7A-4.1
, application procedure, and assistance level;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Employability assessment, work activities, and supportive services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Conditions of continued eligibility, eligibility time limits, eligibility recertification periods, and exemptions;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Program participation requirements, criteria for disqualification, and good cause exemptions;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Disqualification for intentional program violation or failure to comply with program requirements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Benefit recovery and recoupment policies and procedures;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Methods of distribution and payment of moneys appropriated by the Legislature or received from the federal government for the granting of temporary assistance for needy families;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Development of applications, reports, and other forms;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_9">
              <akn:num>(9)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Enforcement of child support obligations including distribution of collections, cooperative agreements with courts and law enforcement officials, and such other rules as may be found necessary or desirable to qualify for federal financial participation;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_10">
              <akn:num>(10)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Collection, audit, and reporting of facts and statistics relating to the field of public assistance;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_11">
              <akn:num>(11)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Compliance with federal reporting and documentation requirements necessary to
qualify for federal funds; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_3__subsec_12">
              <akn:num>(12)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Any other standards of operation and administration within the mandate of this chapter, as necessary or desirable to qualify for federal financial participation.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 4; SL 2020, ch 116, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_4">
            <akn:num>28-7A-4</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Determining eligibility requirements</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-4
.
Determining eligibility requirements.
Eligibility criteria and assistance level for temporary assistance for needy families shall be determined by the department with due regard to the necessary expenditures of families in this state.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 5.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_4_1">
            <akn:num>28-7A-4.1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Exemption--Controlled substance felony--Denial of benefits—Prohibition</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-4.1
.
Exemption--Controlled substance felony--Denial of benefits—Prohibition.
As permitted in accordance with 21 U.S.C. § 862a(d)(1)(A), this state exempts itself from the application of 21 U.S.C. § 862a(a)(1).
The department may not deny benefits otherwise available under this chapter to an applicant solely because the applicant has been convicted, under state or federal law, of an offense that is classified as a felony and which has as an element the possession, use, or distribution of a controlled substance, as defined in §
34-20B-3
or 21 U.S.C. § 802.
Source:
SL 2020, ch 116, § 2.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_5">
            <akn:num>28-7A-5</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Social security number required for eligibility</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-5
.
Social security number required for eligibility.
An applicant for or recipient of assistance under this chapter shall supply proof of or apply for a social security number as a condition of eligibility to receive assistance. The parent or relative with whom the child resides shall comply on behalf of a child for whom assistance is claimed.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 6.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_6">
            <akn:num>28-7A-6</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Cooperation with paternity and child support proceedings required</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-6
.
Cooperation with paternity and child support proceedings required.
An applicant or recipient of assistance under this chapter shall, as a condition of eligibility for assistance, cooperate with proceedings to establish paternity and to enforce, collect, or modify child support on behalf of any child for whom assistance is claimed or received.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 7.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_7">
            <akn:num>28-7A-7</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Assignment of support rights</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-7
.
Assignment of support rights.
Application for or receipt of assistance under this chapter or of foster care maintenance payments under the Title IV-E state plan shall operate as an assignment by operation of law of all support rights from any person, which such applicant or recipient may have on the applicant's or recipient's own behalf or on behalf of any other family member for whom the recipient is receiving assistance or Title IV-E foster care maintenance payments, including any support payments accrued and unpaid at the time of the assignment.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 8.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_8">
            <akn:num>28-7A-8</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Manner of application--Timely response</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-8
.
Manner of application--Timely response.
Application shall be made in a manner prescribed by the department. The department shall promptly notify the applicant of its decision.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 9.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_9">
            <akn:num>28-7A-9</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Assessment of skills, work experience, and employability</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-9
.
Assessment of skills, work experience, and employability.
The department shall make such assessment of the skills, prior work experience, and employability of eligible applicants or recipients as may be necessary and feasible for the purposes of this chapter.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 10.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_10">
            <akn:num>28-7A-10</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Adoption of standards for participation in work activities and assistance programs--Training and education</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-10
.
Adoption of standards for participation in work activities and assistance programs--Training and education.
The department may adopt by rules promulgated pursuant to chapter
1-26
reasonable standards for the participation of eligible recipients in work activities and programs of assistance calculated to foster parental responsibility, employment, or family independence. To the extent possible in a work oriented program, training, and education, although not an alternative for working, may be utilized to prepare people for work.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 11.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_11">
            <akn:num>28-7A-11</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Denial, reduction, or termination of assistance for refusal to participate--Investigation of compliance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-11
.
Denial, reduction, or termination of assistance for refusal to participate--Investigation of compliance.
The department may deny, reduce, or terminate assistance to an applicant or recipient who voluntarily refuses to participate in an assessment, work activity, or assistance program for such period as may be reasonably necessary to deter program waste or abuse. The department may adopt by rules promulgated pursuant to chapter
1-26
necessary and reasonable exemptions and deferrals. The department shall have access to the home of a dependent child at reasonable times for the purpose of conducting such investigation as may be necessary to assure compliance with program requirements.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 12.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_12">
            <akn:num>28-7A-12</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Feasible and reasonable assistance programs authorized</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-12
.
Feasible and reasonable assistance programs authorized.
The department may implement such programs of assistance as may be feasible and reasonably calculated to fulfill the purposes of this chapter. This chapter does not require the department to provide assistance in the absence of legislative appropriation therefor.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 13.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_13">
            <akn:num>28-7A-13</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Employment as work activity</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-13
.
Employment as work activity.
An adult in a family receiving assistance under this chapter may fill a vacant employment position in order to engage in a work activity except no such adult may be employed or assigned if any other individual is on layoff from the same or any substantially equivalent job or if the employer has terminated the employment of any regular employee or otherwise caused an involuntary reduction of its workforce in order to fill the vacancy so created.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 14.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_14">
            <akn:num>28-7A-14</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Reconsideration of assistance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-14
.
Reconsideration of assistance.
The department may reconsider assistance as frequently as may be required. The department may deny, reduce, suspend, or terminate assistance as the circumstances may indicate upon such reconsideration.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 15.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_15">
            <akn:num>28-7A-15</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Appeal by aggrieved applicant or recipient</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-15
.
Appeal by aggrieved applicant or recipient.
An applicant or recipient whose application is denied or not acted upon or who is aggrieved by any action affecting receipt, suspension, reduction, or termination of assistance may appeal the action or inaction as provided in chapter
1-26
.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 16.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_16">
            <akn:num>28-7A-16</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Denial, reduction, or termination of assistance to deter fraud and program abuse</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_16__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Intentionally make or cause to be made any false statement or misrepresentation in any application, report, or other communication with the department; or</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_16__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Having knowledge of any event or circumstance affecting the initial or continued eligibility for assistance, intentionally conceal or fail to disclose that event or circumstance for the purpose of obtaining assistance.
The department may deny, reduce, or terminate assistance to any person or household who has violated this section for such period as may be reasonable or necessary to deter fraud or program abuse.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 17.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_17">
            <akn:num>28-7A-17</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Adoption of policies to recover overpayment of assistance</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-17
.
Adoption of policies to recover overpayment of assistance.
The department may adopt, pursuant to chapter
1-26
, necessary and reasonable policies and procedures to recover or recoup any overpayment of assistance that resulted from fraud or misrepresentation, erroneous determination of eligibility or amount of assistance, or otherwise.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 18.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_18">
            <akn:num>28-7A-18</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Assistance not transferable--Assistance not subject to legal process--Exception</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-18
.
Assistance not transferable--Assistance not subject to legal process--Exception.
Assistance granted under this chapter is not transferable or assignable at law or in equity. No money paid or assistance granted under this chapter is subject to execution, levy, attachment, garnishment, or other legal process, except as may be expressly authorized by law for purposes of recovery or recoupment by the department, or to the operation of any bankruptcy or insolvency law.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 19.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_19">
            <akn:num>28-7A-19</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Effect of amending or repealing acts</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-19
.
Effect of amending or repealing acts.
Assistance implemented under this chapter is subject to the provisions of any amending or repealing act that may hereafter be enacted. No applicant or recipient of assistance under this chapter has any claim for compensation or otherwise by reason of the effect of any such amending or repealing act.
Source:
SL 1997, ch 166, § 20.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_20">
            <akn:num>28-7A-20</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Department to implement combination work and education activity--Time limitation--Goal</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-20
.
Department to implement combination work and education activity--Time limitation--Goal.
The Department of Social Services shall implement a combination work and education activity for recipients of the temporary assistance for needy families program who qualify under the provisions of §§
28-7A-20
to
28-7A-24
, inclusive. This combination work and education activity is limited to twenty
-
four months and must be directed towards a goal of employment that leads to self
-
sufficiency .
Source:
SL 2000, ch 133, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_21">
            <akn:num>28-7A-21</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Combination work and education activity--Criteria for education component</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_21__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Must be an undergraduate postsecondary educational program at an institution accredited by the North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_21__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Must result in a marketable skill directly related to employment;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_21__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Must be related to the available employment demands and opportunities in the recipient's labor market.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 133, § 2.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_22">
            <akn:num>28-7A-22</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Eligibility for work and education activity</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_22__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Must be enrolled in a postsecondary education program for a minimum of twelve credit hours. Credit hours to meet the requirement of this subdivision may not exceed fifteen;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_22__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Must meet the admission requirements established by the institution;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_22__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Must maintain a 2.5 grade point average; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_22__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Must have a combination of work hours and classroom hours that meet the work participation requirements of the state's temporary assistance for needy families program.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 133, § 3.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_23">
            <akn:num>28-7A-23</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Department may limit number of participants in work and education activity</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-7A-23
.
Department may limit number of participants in work and education activity.
The Department of Social Services may limit the number of participants in the work and education activity to meet the requirements under the state's temporary assistance for needy families program.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 133, § 4.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_7A_24">
            <akn:num>28-7A-24</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Promulgation of rules</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_24__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Employability assessment, work activities, and supportive services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_24__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Conditions of continued eligibility, eligibility time limits, eligibility recertification periods, and exemptions;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_24__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Program participation requirements, criteria for disqualification, and good cause exemptions;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_24__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Limits on the number of participants; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_7A_24__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Such other rules and standards of operation and administration within the mandate of §§
28-7A-20
to
28-7A-24
, inclusive, as may be necessary or desirable to qualify for federal financial participation.
Source:
SL 2000, ch 133, § 5.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_8">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-8</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Title XX Social Services Program</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_8_1">
            <akn:num>28-8-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-8-1 to 28-8-22</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-8-1 to 28-8-22.
Repealed by SL 1974, ch 190, § 1</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_8_23">
            <akn:num>28-8-23</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Purposes of chapter</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_23__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Achieving or maintaining self
-
support to prevent, reduce, or eliminate dependency;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_23__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Achieving or maintaining self
-
sufficiency, including reduction of dependency;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_23__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Preventing or remedying neglect, abuse, or exploitation of children and adults unable to protect their own interests, or preserving, rehabilitating, or reuniting families;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_23__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Preventing or reducing inappropriate institutional care by providing for community
-
based care, home
-
based care, or other forms of less intensive care; or</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_23__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Securing referral or admission for institutional care when other forms of care are not appropriate, or providing services to individuals in institutions.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 188, § 1; SL 1980, ch 201, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_8_24">
            <akn:num>28-8-24</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Definition of terms</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_24__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Deleted by SL 2004, ch 167, § 59.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_24__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Department," the Department of Social Services created by §
1-36-1
; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_24__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Secretary," the duly appointed, qualified, and acting head of the department created by §
1-36-2
.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 188, § 2; SL 2004, ch 167, § 59.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_8_25">
            <akn:num>28-8-25</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Powers of department in implementation of program</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_25__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Prepare and submit for approval of the secretary of the United States Department of Health and Human Services, a comprehensive service program plan or plans as the agency of this state under the provisions of Title XX of the federal Social Security Act;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_25__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Serve as the agency within this state which will administer or supervise the administration of the program for the provision of the services authorized under Title XX;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_25__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Comply with the provisions of Title XX and any rules and regulations promulgated pursuant thereto by the federal government for the purposes of qualifying for federal funds and making such reports concerning the use of federal social service funds as may be required by regulation;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_25__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Designate the state's service program year as the fiscal year of either the federal government or state government;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_25__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Accept and use donated private funds as long as such funds are transferred to the department, are under the department's exclusive administrative control, are donated without restriction as to use, other than restrictions by a donor who is not a sponsor or operator of a service program or services to which such funds are restricted, other than restriction as to the geographic area to which the funds are to be used, or other than restrictions which will cause such funds to revert to the donor's facility or use except when the donor's facility is a nonprofit organization;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_25__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Impose a service fee as a precondition to provision of any service specified by the department.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 188, § 3; SL 1980, ch 201, § 2; SL 2004, ch 167, § 60.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_8_26">
            <akn:num>28-8-26</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Services for which fees prohibited--Low-income families</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_26__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Information or informational and referral services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_26__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Any services directed at the goal of preventing or remedying neglect, abuse, or exploitation of minor children or adults unable to protect their own interest;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_26__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Any services provided to or on behalf of any eligible person defined by the department pursuant to Title XX of the Social Security Act; or</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_8_26__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Any services provided to or on behalf of a member of a family, the monthly gross income of which is less than an amount specified by the department, adjusted to take into account the size of the family, as may be required by the federal government.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 188, § 3</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_8_27">
            <akn:num>28-8-27</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Deposit and crediting of nonappropriated funds--Use by department--No reversion to general fund</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-8-27
.
Deposit and crediting of nonappropriated funds--Use by department--No reversion to general fund.
All privately donated funds and other nonappropriated funds shall be deposited with the state treasurer and credited to a program account designated by the department and any such funds are continuously appropriated for use by the Department of Social Services for the purpose of obtaining federal funds available under Title XX of the Social Security Act. No money received by the state treasurer pursuant to this section may revert to the general fund of the state.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 188, § 6; SL 2004, ch 167, § 62.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_8_28">
            <akn:num>28-8-28</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Services provided to individuals by secretary--Rules and standards</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-8-28
.
Services provided to individuals by secretary--Rules and standards.
Subject to rules of the department establishing eligibility for, the content of, and the extent of entitlement to services, with or without a service fee, the secretary of social services may provide services to and on behalf of individuals within this state, and fix standards or other conditions of participation by providers of such services under contract or otherwise.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 188, § 4; SL 2004, ch 167, § 63.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_8_29">
            <akn:num>28-8-29</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Recipient information confidential--Conditions for disclosure</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-8-29
.
Recipient information confidential--Conditions for disclosure.
The use or disclosure of information obtained in connection with the administration of the comprehensive annual service programs concerning applicants for or recipients of such services is confidential and restricted to purposes directly connected with the administration of that program. However, such information may be disclosed with the prior written consent of the applicant or recipient or, if a minor, a parent or guardian, or, in accordance with such rules promulgated by the department, for purposes directly connected with the administration of any other related program.
Source:
SL 1975, ch 188, § 5; SL 2004, ch 167, § 64.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
        <akn:chapter eId="chapter_28_9">
          <akn:num>Chapter 28-9</akn:num>
          <akn:heading>Poor Relief</akn:heading>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_1">
            <akn:num>28-9-1</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-1 to 28-9-22</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-1 to 28-9-22.
Repealed by SL 1974, ch 190, § 1</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_23">
            <akn:num>28-9-23</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Definition of terms</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_23__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Director," the director of rehabilitation services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_23__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Division," the Division of Rehabilitation Services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_23__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>"Vocational rehabilitation" and "vocational rehabilitation services," any goods or services, found by the director to be necessary to render an individual with a disability employable including an assessment for determining eligibility and vocational rehabilitation needs.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 46, § 1; SDC Supp 1960, § 15.08A01; SDCL, § 13-40-1; SL 1975, ch 128, § 269; SL 1993, ch 210, § 1; SL 1997, ch 169, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_24">
            <akn:num>28-9-24</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-24</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-24.
Repealed by SL 1993, ch 210, § 2</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_25">
            <akn:num>28-9-25</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Administration by director</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-25
.
Administration by director.
The Division of Rehabilitation Services shall be administered by the director appointed pursuant to §
1-36A-4
.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 46, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 15.08A03; SDCL, § 13-40-3; SL 1975, ch 128, § 271; SL 1977, ch 226, § 12.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_26">
            <akn:num>28-9-26</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-26</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-26.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, § 2</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_27">
            <akn:num>28-9-27</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Employment of personnel for division</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-27
.
Employment of personnel for division.
The director of rehabilitation services shall employ, in accordance with chapter
3-6D
, personnel as the director deems necessary for the efficient performance of the Division of Rehabilitation Services.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 46, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 15.08A03 (1); SDCL § 13-40-5; SL 1973, ch 101; SL 1975, ch 128, § 273; SL 2018, ch 12, § 10.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_28">
            <akn:num>28-9-28</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-28, 28-9-29</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-28, 28-9-29.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, §§ 3, 4</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_30">
            <akn:num>28-9-30</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Rehabilitation service provided to eligible persons</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-30
.
Rehabilitation service provided to eligible persons.
The Division of Rehabilitation Services shall provide vocational rehabilitation and independent living services to individuals with disabilities determined by the director of rehabilitation services to be eligible.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 46, § 4; SDC Supp 1960, § 15.08A04; SDCL, § 13-40-8; SL 1975, ch 128, § 276; SL 1993, ch 210, § 3; SL 1997, ch 169, § 5.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_31">
            <akn:num>28-9-31</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-31</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-31.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, § 6</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_32">
            <akn:num>28-9-32</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Types of services provided without cost</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_32__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Physical and mental restoration;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_32__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Transportation, for any purpose except when determining the person's eligibility for vocational rehabilitation services and the nature and extent of the services necessary;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_32__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Occupational licenses, tools, equipment, and initial stocks and supplies, excluding computers and computer
-
related devices needed to overcome a disability
-
related impediment to employment;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_32__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Maintenance for any purpose except when determining the person's eligibility for vocational rehabilitation services and the nature and extent of the services necessary;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_32__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Training books and materials; and</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_32__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Tuition and fees for participating in postsecondary academic training programs under the Federal Student Financial Assistance Program.
Source:
SL 1951, § 46, § 8; SDC Supp 1960, § 15.08A08; SDCL, § 13-40-10; SL 1975, ch 128, § 278; SL 1993, ch 210, § 5; SL 1996, ch 185; SL 2001, ch 153, § 1.</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_33">
            <akn:num>28-9-33</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-33</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-33.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, § 7</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_34">
            <akn:num>28-9-34</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-34</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-34.
Repealed by SL 2013, ch 126, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_35">
            <akn:num>28-9-35</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-35</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-35.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, § 8</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_36">
            <akn:num>28-9-36</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Review of determinations of counselors or coordinators--Written final determination by division director</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-36
.
Review of determinations of counselors or coordinators--Written final determination by division director.
The director of the Division of Rehabilitation Services shall establish procedures, pursuant to chapter
1-26
, for the review of any determination made by a rehabilitation counselor or coordinator upon the request of the individual with the disability, or the individual's parents, if the individual is a minor, or the individual's guardian.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 46, § 9; SDC Supp 1960, § 15.08A09; SDCL, § 13-40-13; SL 1975, ch 128, § 282; SL 1981, ch 218, § 1; SL 1989, ch 21, § 147; SL 1993, ch 210, § 8; SL 2001, ch 154, § 1.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_37">
            <akn:num>28-9-37</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-37 to 28-9-39</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-37 to 28-9-39.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, §§ 9 to 11</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_40">
            <akn:num>28-9-40</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Agreements to implement federal statutes--Administration--Compliance with federal requirements</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-40
.
Agreements to implement federal statutes--Administration--Compliance with federal requirements.
The Division of Rehabilitation Services shall make agreements or plans to cooperate with the United States in carrying out the purposes of any federal statutes pertaining to vocational rehabilitation. The division may adopt such methods of administration as are found by the United States to be necessary for the proper and efficient operation of such agreements or plans. The division may comply with such conditions as may be necessary to secure the full benefits of such federal statutes.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 46, § 5; SDC Supp 1960, § 15.08A05; SDCL, § 13-40-17; SL 1975, ch 128, § 286.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_41">
            <akn:num>28-9-41</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-41</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-41.
Repealed by SL 1993, ch 210, § 10</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_42">
            <akn:num>28-9-42</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-42, 28-9-43</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-42, 28-9-43.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, §§ 12, 13</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_44">
            <akn:num>28-9-44</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Rules for division--Scope of rules</akn:heading>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_1">
              <akn:num>(1)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>The protection of records and confidential information;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_2">
              <akn:num>(2)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Application requirements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_3">
              <akn:num>(3)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Eligibility requirements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_4">
              <akn:num>(4)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Income and resource requirements;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_5">
              <akn:num>(5)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Administration and operation of vocational rehabilitation and independent living programs;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_6">
              <akn:num>(6)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Grant applications and awards;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_7">
              <akn:num>(7)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Administrative reviews and fair hearings;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_8">
              <akn:num>(8)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Amount, scope, and duration of rehabilitative services and independent living services;</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
            <akn:subsection eId="sec_28_9_44__subsec_9">
              <akn:num>(9)</akn:num>
              <akn:content>
                <akn:p>Fees.
Source:
SL 1951, ch 46, § 3; SDC Supp 1960, § 15.08A03</akn:p>
              </akn:content>
            </akn:subsection>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_45">
            <akn:num>28-9-45</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-45</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-45.
Repealed by SL 1982, ch 16, § 22</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_46">
            <akn:num>28-9-46</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>28-9-46</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-46.
Repealed by SL 1997, ch 169, § 14</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_47">
            <akn:num>28-9-47</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Advisory Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities designated</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-47
.
Advisory Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities designated.
The Board of Vocational Rehabilitation is hereby designated as the Governor's Advisory Committee on Employment of People with Disabilities and shall perform the duties of the committee.
Source:
SL 1967, ch 270, § 1; SL 1989, ch 444, § 2; SL 1997, ch 297, § 1; SDCL §
60-7-1
; SL 2008, ch 276, § 67</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
          <akn:section eId="sec_28_9_48">
            <akn:num>28-9-48</akn:num>
            <akn:heading>Repealed by SL 2012, ch 14, §§ 3, 4</akn:heading>
            <akn:content>
              <akn:p>28-9-48
, 28-9-49.
Repealed by SL 2012, ch 14, §§ 3, 4.</akn:p>
            </akn:content>
          </akn:section>
        </akn:chapter>
      </akn:part>
    </akn:body>
  </akn:act>
</akn:akomaNtoso>